<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The saints communion with God, and Gods communion with them in ordinances. As it was delivered in severall sermons / by that faithfull servant of Christ, Mr. William Strong, late minister at Westminster.</title>
            <author>Strong, William, d. 1654.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1655</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 170 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 117 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A94069</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing S6006</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E1693_2</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R209425</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99868307</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99868307</idno>
            <idno type="VID">170270</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A94069)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 170270)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 211:E1693[2])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The saints communion with God, and Gods communion with them in ordinances. As it was delivered in severall sermons / by that faithfull servant of Christ, Mr. William Strong, late minister at Westminster.</title>
                  <author>Strong, William, d. 1654.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[14], 212 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for George Sawbridge at the Bible on Ludgate-hill, and Ro: Gibbs in Chancery Lane.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London, :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1656. [i.e. 1655]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "23 Nouemb: 1655."; the second 6 in the imprint date has been crossed out.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
               <term>Lord's Supper --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-09</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-09</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-11</date>
            <label>Jayanthi Reddy</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-11</date>
            <label>Jayanthi Reddy</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:170270:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE SAINTS COMMUNION With GOD, And GODS Communion with them in ORDINANCES. As it was delivered in Severall SERMONS</p>
            <p>By that Faithfull ſervant of Chriſt, Mr. <hi>WILLIAM STRONG,</hi> Late Miniſter at <hi>Weſtminſter.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>George Sawbridge</hi> at the Bible on <hi>Ludgate-hill,</hi> and <hi>Ro: Gibbs.</hi> in <hi>Chancery Lane.</hi> 1656.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:170270:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:170270:2"/>
            <head>To his Honourable friend, Collonell <hi>William Purefoy,</hi> Recorder of the famous City of <hi>Coventry.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>SIR,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>His Book falling by Providence into my hands, and the earneſt intreaty of divers Chriſtian and pious friends in <hi>London,</hi> having drawn from me the Epiſtle to the Reader, as alſo having heard much of your being an admirer of the Author here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of (Reverend Maſter <hi>Strong,</hi> now bleſſed in the Eternall Manſions above) I made bold to commend the book alſo to
<pb facs="tcp:170270:3"/>your ſelfe, as an humble ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledgment of the faithfull ſervice I owe you, by the ſame way of fellowſhip and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion in Goſpell-Ordinan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, with the Father, and his Son Jeſus Chriſt our Lord: we muſt all attain to that bleſſed and eternall communion, where the preſence of God &amp; Chriſt in glory, ſhall tranſcend the pureſt Ordinances here below. But if either we turn our backs upon holy and pre<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tious truths received, and once publickly profeſſed, or let our zeal cool, or by ſitting ſtill go not forward, we both loſe the comfort of communion here, and ſhall have leſſe communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on in glory. No doubt, Sir, but it is a wild age wherein we live; many ſtupendious chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, ſtrange turnings, and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mazing
<pb facs="tcp:170270:3"/>alterations we have ſeen, both in Church and State, and who knowes what yet any of us muſt undergo; we have therefore more need to ſtick to our principles, more faithfully to own Gods name, and to maintain our practiſe in holineſſe with more vigor and conſtancy, that in the end we may reap, if we faint not. Which that you, Sir, my Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable friend, may ſtill per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form, and bring a greater glory to God, and do more good to that my native City of <hi>Coven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try,</hi> where I was once an un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthy Lecturer, and to the whole Country better ſervice, ſhining more gloriouſly in the end of your daies; that ſo when you have finiſhed your courſe with joy, and kept the faith, the houre of temptation
<pb facs="tcp:170270:4"/>which now is upon all the earth, that then you may re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive the Crown laid up for you, which your Son &amp; Wife, now both bleſſed and glorious, are enjoying to all eternity, is, and ſhall be the hearty and earneſt prayer of him, who doubts not of your candid ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptation of this my bold pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumption, but deſires in all things ever to be found,</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>Sir</salute>
               <signed>Your moſt humble and faithfull ſervant upon the beſt ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compt,JOHN HERING.</signed>
               <dateline>
                  <hi>From my Study Brides-Church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yard, London.</hi>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:170270:4"/>
            <opener>
               <salute>Chriſtian Reader,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>T the earneſt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treaty and requeſt of ſome Pious and Chriſtian Friends, who finde ſweet Communion with God in Goſpell-Ordinances, I am bold to commend the reading of this book unto thee: The Author hereof I believe is now in Heaven, receiving his wages after his work is done; and a glorified Saint,
<pb facs="tcp:170270:5"/>enjoying eternall Communion with God above Ordinan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces. We muſt all confeſſe, that in reſpect of human frailties, we are not ſo STRONG, but that weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe will attend the best of us, whileſt here below in our pilgrimage to that Heavenly <hi>Canaan:</hi> He will be much deceived, that reckons this World his Heaven, but doth, and will finde it his Wilder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and at beſt, but his paſſage through the Red-Sea; and here we have need of <hi>Moſes,</hi> not only to kill the Aegyptian for us, and to
<pb facs="tcp:170270:5"/>bring us out of <hi>Egypt;</hi> and alſo lift up his Rod, and ſtretch forth his Hand, and ſo divide the Red-Sea, that our paſſage may be ſafe; but alſo of a <hi>Joſhua</hi> to bring us into <hi>Canaan,</hi> and this is our Lord Jeſus Christ, who is God bleſſed for evermore. No true Saint in this life can live without or above Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances, no more then the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall body can live without food and raiment. God in his infinite wiſdome and mercy, hath admitted the Churches new born babes in all ages to Ordinances, whereby
<pb facs="tcp:170270:6"/>Grace, and the ſeeds of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>generation may be, through mercy, conveyed to them: and are not Saints to the end of their daies perfected by them alſo, as the Apoſtle ſpeaks, <hi>Epheſ. 5.26, 27.</hi> Some waters are contained in Springs and Wells, ſome in Conduits and Pipes, and ſome alſo in the main Ocean; yet they are all conveyances of Water for the ſeveral uſes of the ſonnes of men; and they are all bounded within their due limits: And ſo it is with Goſpell Ordinances; there's the Wells and ſprings of life,
<pb facs="tcp:170270:6"/>there's the Pipes of ſpiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all Comfort, and there's the Ocean of mercy, and all the priviledges of free Grace conveyed to the believing ſoule. All thoſe in theſe li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>centious daies (which God will require ſome where) that cry down Ordinances are forc'd themſelves to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſe new waies of conveying their apprehended ſpirit un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to us. And ſhould we refuſe the waies of Gods own ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointment? Whereever God ſhall record his Name, ſhall we deny to worſhip him there? How then will God
<pb facs="tcp:170270:7"/>come unto us, and bleſſe us, as he hath promiſed? Let thoſe wild men of this Age, that have been at <hi>Jericho</hi> in ſtead of <hi>Ieruſalem,</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolve the queſtion, how the Lord will appear in waies and Ordinances that are not of his own inſtitution and allowance? Will he not ſadly, perſonally, and publickly ſay to them at the great day, who hath required theſe things at your hands? bring no more vain oblations.</p>
            <p>Reader, I will ſay no more, but beſeech thee to turn thy reading into prayer, and thy
<pb facs="tcp:170270:7"/>praying into humble and holy practiſe, that thou maiſt know the Trinity in <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity, and <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity in Trinity, which reaſon cannot underſtand, and maiſt enjoy ſoule-Communion with all the Perſons in the Trinity by Faith in Goſpell-Ordinances; and that both in the Temple, and alſo in every Adminiſtration of the Lord Jeſus to thee, thou maiſt cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dially, affectionately, and with comfort ſay, <hi>Iehovah Shammah,</hi> the Lord is there: And with <hi>Iacob</hi> in his Pil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grimage be able to confeſſe, Surely the Lord is in this
<pb facs="tcp:170270:8"/>place, though ſometimes I knew it not through mine own default. And that thou maiſt finde all mercies and glories bottomed on thy ſpirituall Communion with God, recon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciled to thee in Chriſt thy Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deemer, is the deſire of him, who thirſts after more Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion with God and Chriſt in holy Ordinances, and begs alwaies to be found upon a ſpirituall account</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Thine in the Lord Chriſt, IOHN HERING.</signed>
               <dateline>
                  <hi>From my Study in</hi> Brides <hi>Church-yard</hi> London, <date>Octo. <hi>27. 1655.</hi>
                  </date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:170270:8"/>
            <head>The Saints Communion with God, and Gods Communion with them in O dinances.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>Exod. 20.24. The latter part.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>In all places where I record my name, (or where I cauſe my name to be remembred,) I will come unto thee, and I will bleſſe thee.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <div n="1-55" type="pages">
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He whole Chapter is made up of Gods giving the morall Law: In the gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving forth of which law there are many remarkable paſſages; as why it muſt be given from Mount <hi>Sinai?</hi> why immedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ately after their deliverance out of <hi>Egypt?</hi> why in thunde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rings and lightnings? why the world in its infancy lived
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:170270:9"/>without a law written? Theſe things I have already ſpoken to. The words which I have read are a promiſe made unto the places of Gods publique worſhip, which were typicall, for reſpect to places is done a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way, <hi>John</hi> 4.21. <hi>The houre com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth when ye ſhall neither in this mountaine, nor yet at Jeruſalem worſhip the Father.</hi> All acts of worſhip are to be done to God as a Father, &amp; reſpect of places beeing done away, now chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren may every where wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip their Father. The whole Jewiſh Religion lay in theſe 4. things. 1. In holy times. 2. In holy places. 3. In holy perſons 4. In holy things. The Apoſtle 1 <hi>Jam.</hi> 27. hath wrapt up a Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> under the new Teſtame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t; <hi>pure Religion and underfiled be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore God, and the Father is this, To
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:170270:9"/>viſit the Fatherleſſe and widdowes in their afflictions, and keepe him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe unſpotted from the world.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Jeſus Chriſt was made known foure waies in the old Teſtament, by promiſes, by prophecies, by Types &amp; ſhad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dowes, &amp; by Apparition. The bleſſing in this Text comes under an Apparition, for it is nothing elſe but the appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance of God in divine Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances, now reſpect to places being done away by the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mulgation of the Goſpell. The promiſe, though it doe not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late to the place, yet it doth re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late to the Ordinances, ſo that in all places, if you lift up holy hands without wrath and doubting, and worſhip the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in ſpirit, this bleſſing be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longs to you. <hi>In all places where I record my name, &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:170270:10"/>
               <p>The words themſelves be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a promiſe have theſe par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticulars in them.</p>
               <list>
                  <item>Firſt, the Author of it, that's God the Father.</item>
                  <item>Secondly, the extent of it; and that is all places where I record my name.</item>
                  <item>Thirdly, the nature of the promiſe, and that in two branches.
<list>
                        <item>1. Of communion, I will come unto you.</item>
                        <item>2. Of benediction, I will bleſſe you.</item>
                     </list>
                  </item>
               </list>
               <p>Wherein you have 3. things.</p>
               <list>
                  <item>1. The union of them, mee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting and bleſſing.</item>
                  <item>2. The order of them, firſt meeting, and then bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing.</item>
                  <item>3. The Object of them, (the ſincere ſeekers of God) I will come unto thee and
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:170270:10"/>I will bleſſe thee.</item>
               </list>
               <p>Ther's but one thing in the Text that is difficult.</p>
               <p>In the place where I record my name, In the Hebrew tis <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>becol hammakom aſher azkir etſhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ni;</hi> that is, In every place where I ſhall cauſe or make my name to bee remembred; or in every place where I ſhall mention (or make mention) of my name: for the word <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>azkir</hi> is in the conjuga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion <hi>hiphil,</hi> which uſually im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ports an action done or cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to be done by another, as here, I will cauſe to bee re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membred, the name of God hath ſeverall acceptations in Scripture; By name of God is here meant the publique wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip and ſervice of God, <hi>Jer.</hi> 7.12. <hi>Goe yee tó</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>Shil<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>h, the
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:170270:11"/>place where I have ſet my name</hi> that is, my worſhip &amp; ſervice. So its ſaid <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>Jehovah echad uſhemo echad. Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hovah ſhall be one, and his name one,</hi> that is, he ſhall be ſo wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhipped as he is one in eſſence. In all places where I record my name I will meet you and bleſſe you.</p>
               <p>For the explication and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmation of the two chiefe heads the text points at, viz. 1. That by recording, remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bring or mentioning the name of God, is meant, the ſetting up the worſhip of God in his Ordinances and 2. that where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever the name of God is thus recorded, remembred, or mentioned; that is, whereſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever God is worſhipped in his Ordinances, there hee doth promiſe and command a bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing;
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:170270:11"/>or there he will meet thoſe that record his name, in the worſhipping of himſelfe, with a bleſſing. There are two or three other parallell places of Scripture deſerving ſpeciall conſideration; as 1. for the firſt point, there is a moſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>markable expreſſion, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 22.27. All the nations of the world (<gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>Jizkeru,</hi> the ſame Hebrew root with <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>azkir,</hi> here in the Text) ſhall remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber; why, what is that? or what ſhall they remember? even this, they ſhall turne to the Lord and worſhip him his name in his Ordinances; as is explained in the words fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing of the verſe; And all the families of the nations <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>jiſhtachavu</hi>) ſhall (bow downe themſelves, or) worſhip before thee, &amp;c. and ſo <hi>Pſalme</hi>
                  <pb n="8" facs="tcp:170270:12"/>86.4. All nations whom thou haſt made, ſhall come, (<gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>Vejiſhtachavu</hi>) and they ſhall worſhip before thee; And how ſhall they doe ſo? even by recording, remembring, &amp; making mention of the glory of thy name; as in the words following, (<gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>Vicab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedu liſhmecha</hi>) and they ſhall glorifie thy name. 2. For the ſecond point, that the Lord (as he hath promiſed, ſo he) doth come and meet thoſe with a bleſſing, who doe thus glorifie and worſhip his name in his Ordinances, ſo that they ſhall never doe it in vaine, and for nothing; ſee thoſe two preci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous texts in <hi>Iſaiah</hi> his prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie, <hi>viz. Jſa.</hi> 64.5. &amp; 45.19. firſt in <hi>Iſaiah</hi> 64. <hi>v.</hi> 4. The incom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehenſible mercies and good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of God, which he hath
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:170270:12"/>laid up and prepared for his people, is ſet forth; ſince the beginning of the world, men have not perceived by eare, neither hath the eye ſeen, &amp;c. And then marke what fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loweth, verſe 5. Where the Prophet deſcribeth thoſe, who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the Lord will come and meet with all thoſe incomprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible bleſſings, viz. Thoſe who waite upon him, and rejoyce in his worſhip, working righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſſe, and remembring his name in his waies and Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinances; Thou meereſt him that rejoyceth and worketh righteouſneſſe, thoſe who re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member thee in thy waies, &amp;c. So that no leſſe then bleſſings incomprehenſible by the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding &amp; minde of man, do waite upon thoſe who wait upon God, &amp; who remember
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:170270:13"/>his name in his worſhip, waies and Ordinances; And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore that other cited text <hi>Iſa.</hi> 45.9. is fully verified; that never did any of the ſonnes of <hi>Jacob</hi> (true Iſraelites) ſeeke God (in his waies, worſhip and ordinances) in vain; I ſaid not unto the ſeed of <hi>Jacob,</hi> ſeek ye me in vaine, or for a void or empty nothing, as the word <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>tohu</hi> importeth; no, the ſincere ſeekers of God, in his worſhip &amp; ordinances, ſhal not be ſent away with <hi>tohu,</hi> vacui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty and emptineſſe; but with their cup overflowing with all the fulneſſe of incomprehenſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble bleſſings. Thus doth the Lord come and meet them with a bleſſing who remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber his name in his worſhip and ordinances; in all places where I record my name, I
<pb facs="tcp:170270:13"/>will meet you and bleſſe you. But we are to conſider, that in relation to Ordinances, there be foure ſorts of men.</p>
               <p n="1">1. Some they are altogether below Ordinances.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Others are altogether a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove Ordina<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ces, they look up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on them as milke fit for babes, but not as meat fit for ſtrong men: they looke upon them as the ſhadwes of the evening, fit to be ſtretched over the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, whoſe knowledge is not very high, 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.19. <hi>We have a more ſure word of Propheſie, where unto ye do well that ye take heed, as unto a light that ſhineth in a darke place, until the day dawn, &amp; the day ſtar ariſe in your hearts.</hi> They think that all theſe morning ſtarrs muſt away as ſoone as e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver Jeſus Chriſt hath riſen as a Sun in the Heart of the Saints.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:170270:14"/>
               <p n="3">3. Others, they are ſuch as take up their reſt in Ordinan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, and conclude the good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of their eſtate by Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances, becauſe they have the enjoyment of Ordinances, therefore they thinke they have the enjoyment of God.</p>
               <p n="4">4. Others neither reſt in, nor yet reſt from Ordinances, and theſe are perſons indeede that are like to meet with a bleſſing when they come to God, when theſe come to worſhip him, they are made welcome to him, and they shall be bleſſed by him; ſuch a ſpirit is fit for Ordinances, and ſuch a ſpirit shall receive much bleſſing by Ordinances.</p>
               <p>The propoſitions that lie in the words are theſe.</p>
               <p n="1">1.
<label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Doct. </seg>1</label> One of the principall ends which God aimes at in the
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:170270:14"/>ſetting up of his publique Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinances, is, that he may have Communion with his Saints, and that his Saints may have communion with him.</p>
               <p n="2">2. The times of a Saints Communion with God,
<label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Doct. </seg>2</label> and Gods Communion with them are times of bleſſing, and times of benediction.</p>
               <p>Communion times are bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed times, and they are bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing times. Bleſſednes is out of the reach of the whole Cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ation, one Creature cannot make another bleſſed, nay all the creatures cannot make one creature bleſſed; Man is fallen too low for his fellow creature to advance him; He is too ſore for the whole creation to make him a plaſter. Tis impoſſible for the whole creation to make any part of amends to
<pb facs="tcp:170270:15"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="13" facs="tcp:170270:15"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="14" facs="tcp:170270:16"/>man for the wrong that he did himſelfe; creatures cannot take off that curſe which they lye under themſelves, how then can they give the bleſſing that's wanting to others? no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing is in working above what 'tis in being, the world in being is poore and begger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, therefore it can never make us rich, <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 2.21. <hi>I will heare the heavens, &amp; they ſhall heare the earth, &amp;c.</hi> The heavens they cry to God, the earth that cries to the heavens, the crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures they cry to the earth; ſtill we are led up the Stairs by one creature to another, till wee have paſt through them all to God himſelfe, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in indeed doth our bleſſedneſs lie; creatures want a bleſſed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe for themſelves, how can they give a bleſſedneſs unto us?</p>
               <pb n="15" facs="tcp:170270:16"/>
               <p n="3">3. Doctrine that might bee raiſed from the words, viz. That the foundation of all the bleſſedneſſe of man is the will of God; I will meet them and bleſſe them. But 'tis the firſt of theſe I ſhall ſpeake of, viz.</p>
               <p>Doct. <hi>That one of the princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pall ends which God aimes at in the ſetting up of his publique Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances, is, that he may have com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion with the Saints, and that his Saints might have communion with him.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Every man while he lives here is at a diſtance from God, there's a twofold diſtance that is between God and the crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures. Firſt, a diſtance in point of Reconciliation. 2<hi rend="sup">ly,</hi> a di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance in point of communion: there's a Naturall diſtance as we are creatures, and a mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall diſtance as we are ſinners.</p>
               <pb n="16" facs="tcp:170270:17"/>
               <p>I shall premiſe three things.</p>
               <p n="1">1. The Scripture holds forth ſuch a ſtate.</p>
               <p n="2">2. The Communion that the Saints have with God, it is with all the perſons in the Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity.</p>
               <p n="3">3. That this Communion in this life is chiefly in Ordinan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces.</p>
               <p>Firſt Poſition;
<label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Poſition. </seg>1</label> That the Scripture holds forth ſuch a ſtate of Communion between God and his people, ſuch as is between the Bride and the Bridegroome in the Bride<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chamber. 'Tis true I confeſſe, all godlines is a myſtery, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.16. <hi>Great is the myſtery of godli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe,</hi> but yet in this there are ſome myſteries greater then o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers: Obſerve there is ſuch an intimacy ſpoken of, 1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 1.3. <hi>Our fellowſhip is with the Father &amp;
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:170270:17"/>with his ſonne Ieſus Chriſt.</hi> Then the Saints have a fellowship with the Father and with Chriſt, yet notwithſtanding ſom of them have a more pecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liar fellowship with God then others. 'Tis true, whoſoever he be that is taken into union, is taken into communion too all the Saints having a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion with themſelves have a communion with Chriſt al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo, for they doe all meet as one with him, as lines in the cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter: yet there are ſome Saints in this life have a more pecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liat communion with the Lord then others; <hi>Numb.</hi> 12.8. <hi>&amp;c. If there be a Prophet</hi> (ſaith God) <hi>I will ſpeake to him in a dreame, in a viſion, but my ſervant Moſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s,</hi> 'tis no ſo with him, <hi>I will ſpeake to him mouth to mouth as a man to his friend, and the
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:170270:18"/>ſimilitude of God ſhall hee behold;</hi> He ſhall have ſuch diſcove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries of God as ordinary Saints have not, hee ſhall have ſuch communion with God as or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary beleevers have not.</p>
               <p>Now this communion of God with the Saints, will ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare to be a very great and glorious intimacy and famili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>arity, if you looke to the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verall denominations that are given to them in the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, all of them imply a very great familiarity; As</p>
               <p n="1">1. They are called his friends, <hi>Abraham</hi> was called the friend of God, <hi>Jam.</hi> 2.23. <hi>I have not called you ſervants, but I have called you friends, John</hi> 15.16. And as Jeſus Chriſt calls them friends, ſo they call him friend too, <hi>Cant.</hi> 5.6. <hi>This is my beloved, &amp; this is my friend O daughters of
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:170270:18"/>Ieruſalem.</hi> What is a friend? truly it is as a mans owne ſelfe, <hi>Deut.</hi> 13.6. <hi>thy friend which is as thine owne ſoule;</hi> Then friend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip ſpeaks high familiarity, <hi>Auſtin</hi> ſpeakes of himſelfe concerning a friend of his, when he died, he profeſſed he was put into a great ſtreight, whether hee himſelfe ſhould be willing to live, or willing to die: hee was unwilling to live, becauſe one halfe of him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe was dead, yet he was not willing to die, becauſe his friend did partly live in him though he were dead.</p>
               <p n="2">2. He doth call the Church, the Bride, the Lambs wife. There is the ſame reſemblance between Chriſt &amp; his Church, as between man &amp; wife; Now you know husband and wife become one fleſh, ſo that this
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:170270:19"/>matrimoniall union is but a ſhaddow and reſemblance of the glorious union that is betwixt Chriſt and his Church: there is a great deale of intimacy betwixt man &amp; his wife, therefore ſhe is cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led <hi>Deut.</hi> 13.6. <hi>the wiſe of his boſome,</hi> now what is the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome? 'tis the ſeate of ſecrecy, and the ſeat of intimacy: For this cauſe the Lord: Jeſus Chriſt is ſaid to be in the <hi>bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>e of the Father, Iohn</hi> 1.18. as one that is acquainted with all his ſecrets, and as one that enjoyes the moſt intimate fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miliarity with the Father. So thou art the wife of the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome of Chriſt. This I think to be the meaning of that, <hi>Lu.</hi> 16.23. It is ſaid <hi>Lazarus died and was carried into Abrahams boſom: Dives</hi> when he dyed was in hell
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:170270:19"/>torments: ſurely then the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther was in heaven, why is it called <hi>Abrahams</hi> boſome? it is a place of reſt, and a place of love. All the Saints being <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brahams</hi> children are of <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hams</hi> Covenant and promiſe, they are received into <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hams boſome</hi> in glory with a great deale of love, and are ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken into his boſome as into the reſting place. Thus the Children of God ſtand in the ſame relation to Chriſt as a wife to the husband.</p>
               <p n="3">3. There is yet a higher ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion of Intimacy then this, all theſe are but externall and fleſhly, but the vnion of the Spirit is much more ſtrong, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6.17. <hi>He that is joyned to the Lord is one Spirit:</hi> He that is joyned to the fleſh is one fleſh, but hee that is joyned to the
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:170270:20"/>Lord is one ſpirit, 'tis as if there were an union of two ſoules. <hi>Cyprian</hi> when he would expreſſe this union, ſaith, <hi>'tis a union of wills, and a confederacy of affections,</hi> they grow into one ſpirit: Theſe relations do im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port thus much, for the Lord Jeſus Chriſt doth not give empty Titles.</p>
               <p>It will further appeare if you conſider thoſe high Acts of Intimacy that the Scripture ſpeakes of, I will name foure.</p>
               <p n="1">1. Chriſt and his people are ſaid to walke together: Chriſt <hi>walkes in them, Revel.</hi> 2.1. <hi>hee walks among them.</hi> 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6.16. and wee reade <hi>of Galleries in which the King is held, Cant.</hi> 7.5. what be thoſe Galleries? places of intimate converſe, where friends walke together, and enjoy communion one with
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:170270:20"/>another, now <hi>can two walke te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether except they be agreed? Amos</hi> 3.3. walking implies intima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy and familiarity.</p>
               <p n="2">2. They ſupp together; now to eate and drinke together in Scripture is an expreſsion of great familiarity, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſaith the Apoſtle <hi>with ſuch an one eate not;</hi> that is, withdraw familiarity: not to eate with one is an Argument of with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drawing familiarity, but to eat together is an argument of familiarity, <hi>Revel.</hi> 3.21. <hi>I will come to him and ſup with him, and he with me.</hi> And for this cauſe, when the Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>munion of Saints is ſet forth, it is ſet forth by eating and drinking together at the ſame table, <hi>we being many are one bread and one body,</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10.17. we are many in number (as <hi>Eraſmus</hi> hath it) but by the
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:170270:21"/>conſent of our ſpirits, wee be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come one bread: when the Lord would expreſſe the inti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>macy the Saints have with him, then he is ſaid to ſup with them and they with him, and marke how hee doth cheere them up, <hi>Cant.</hi> 5.1. <hi>Eate O friends, drinkeye, drinke ye abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dantly O ye beloved.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="3">3. They doe not onely ſup together, but they dwell to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether; <hi>Chriſt dwells in your hearts by feith, Epheſ.</hi> 3.17. It is the great command the Lord laies upon the husband, hee muſt dwell with his wife, now if Jeſus Chriſt will undertake the Relation of a husband, hee muſt dwell with his ſpouſe. In <hi>Iohn</hi> 14.23. he tells you he will fulfill his relation, <hi>I will come to you, and make my abode with you,</hi> as if the Lord could never
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:170270:21"/>ſpeake enough, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6.16. <hi>I will dwell in them, and I will wake among them.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="4">4. They doe not only dwell together, but they lie toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther: Chriſt and his people lie in one bed, <hi>Cant.</hi> 1.16. <hi>Our bed is green;</hi> 'tis not <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>grar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeni,</hi> my bed, but <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>grar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenu,</hi> our bed, what is that? truly they are thoſe Ordinan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of worſhip in which the Lord together with his people doth exerciſe thoſe high Acts of intimacy and familiarity; that will appeare if you com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare it with 57. <hi>Iſay</hi> 7.8. <hi>Thou ſetteſt thy bed upon a high moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine, and thither thou wenteſt up to offer ſacrifices, thou haſt enlar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged thy bed, &amp;c.</hi> what is that? <hi>Floreli<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s</hi> upon the place, faith it was Idolatrous worſhip, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in they did commit ſpirituall
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:170270:22"/>Adultery; now the Lord calls that the bed, Idolatrous Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinances are the bed of Idols: ſo on the other ſide, the bed wherein the Lord Chriſt and his people enjoy intimacy and familiarity is the bed of Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances; and for this cauſe the Church glories in this <hi>Cant.</hi> 1.13. <hi>he ſhall lie all night between my breſts.</hi> So much for the firſt thing I promiſed, namely, that the Scripture holds forth ſuch ſuch a ſtate of Communion between God and his people; I ſhal but name the other two, and ſo paſſe on.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Poſit. </seg>2</label> The ſecond Poſition, The Communion that the Saints have with God, it is with all the perſons: they have not onely Communion with the Father, but Communion with the Son, and not onely com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:170270:22"/>with the Son, but with the Spirit alſo, with all perſons in the Trinity, the people of God have commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie, 1 <hi>John</hi> 1.3. <hi>Truly our fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowſhip is with the Father, and his Sonne Jeſus Chriſt. The</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Poſit. </seg>3</label> Third Poſition, that this communion in this life is chief<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in Ordinances, for the Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediate communion is reſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved for another world: All the communion wee have in this world, it is a mediate com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion, there are mediums betwixt us and God, through which God conveyes grace unto us, and drawes us up un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to him. Ordinances, they are the Galleries, there's the wall of ſinne, and ther's the win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dowes of Odinances; he ſtands behind our wall of ſin, but hee lookes through the windowes
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:170270:23"/>of Ordinances.</p>
               <p>For the opening of this I ſhall ſhew you what fellow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip with God in Ordinances meanes: And firſt, I ſhall lay down ſome Scripturall proofs of this, that the main ende of God in ſetting up Ordinances is, that he may be glorified in communion with his people, and then ſome Poſitions for the right underſtanding of this communion; and after that I ſhall give you the grounds, the properties, the Acts, and the ends of communion, and then apply the whole.</p>
               <p n="1">
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Proof </seg>1</label> 1. Let me prove it from ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture expreſſions, that end that Gods aimes at by ſetting up his Ordinances is, that hee might have communion with the Saints, and his Saints have communion with him: See
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:170270:23"/>
                  <hi>Revel.</hi> 21.3. When God comes to reforme his ordinances, and to purge his Church <hi>I heard a great v<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>yce ſaying, behold the Tabernacle of God is with men, and he will dwell with them:</hi> The Tabernacle and Temple were places of publique worſhip, it was his dwelling and his walking with them; dwelling notes conſtancie, and walk<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing notes familiarity, he will be conſtant, and he will be fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miliar with his people in Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinances. 48. <hi>Ezec</hi> laſt. <hi>And the name of the Citty ſhall bee the LORD is there:</hi> 'Tis a prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie that receives it's accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliſhment, when Jews and Gentiles ſhall bee brought to worſhip God; now when theſe two shall be made one in the hand of the Lord, then shall the name of the City be called
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:170270:24"/>
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>Jehovah ſhaumah; that is, the Lord is there.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Proofe. </seg>2</label> 2. Proofe: This hath been the great ground of all the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parations that the Saints have made; when they have appro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched to God in Ordinances, that they might have commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion with God in them; 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 30.18. <hi>The Lord pardon every one that prepares his heart to ſeeke God, though not according to the purification of the Sanctuary.</hi> As a Bride prepares her ſelfe for her Bridegroom, ſo doe the Saints prepare to meet with God in ordinances, they trim up their laps to meet the Bridegroome. So <hi>Heb.</hi> 10.22. <hi>Let us draw neere, &amp;c. Cant.</hi> 4.16. <hi>Awake, O North winde, and come thou South, blow upon my gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den, that the ſpices thereof may blow out:</hi> and then it followes, <hi>let my
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:170270:24"/>beloved come into his garden, and eate his pleaſant fruit;</hi> They beg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged a North winde for ripe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, and the South winde for refreshing of all their fruits; but for what end? for no other, but that her beloved might come into his garden, &amp; that he might taſt his pleaſant fruit.</p>
               <p n="3">
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Proofe. </seg>3</label> 3. Proofe: The end why God ſets up his Ordinances a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt a people to whom hee will shew mercy, is certaine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly this, that he will meet with them, and have communion with them in theſe ordinan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces; becauſe, for God to with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>draw his fellowship and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> when the Saints of God are in acts of worſhip before him, is threatned as one of the greateſt judgements, <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 5.6. <hi>They ſhall goe with their flocks and herds to ſeeke the Lord, but they
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:170270:25"/>ſhal not finde him for he hath with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drawn himſelfe from them;</hi> that is, they ſhould go to Acts of pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique worſhip; ah but they ſhould enjoy no co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>munion nor ſocietie nor fellowſhip with God, for he had withdrawn himſelf from them, when they drew neere to him, he ſhould draw back from them, hee ſhould leave them to the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked uſe of Ordinances, which was one of the greateſt curſes in the world. Alas what, ſapp or ſweetneſſe can be found in an Ordinance that is appoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by God, if God himſelfe who is the ſweetnes of all Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinances be withdrawne from them? Hence then doe theſe poſitions clearly follow.</p>
               <p n="1">
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Poſit. </seg>1</label> 1. Poſition: In all theſe or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinances, wherein you come before God and meet not with
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:170270:25"/>him, they are all in vaine. To converſe with Ordinances, and not to converſe with God, to have to doe with Ordinances, &amp; not to have to do with God, alas, they are but dry breſts, &amp; a miſcarrying wombe, that wil never bring forth the fruits of holineſſe. Ordinances with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out God are but like bones that have no marrow in them, they are but like ſhells with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out a kernell; your hearing will be vaine, and your hearing will be in vaine; your pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing vaine, and your praying will be in vaine: There will be no ſpirit moving, no voice anſwering, no heart war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mings, no ſoule-refreſhings, n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> God-meetings. It's a ſad thing for God to do theſe two things: firſt, to leave Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances to men. Secondly, to
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:170270:26"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="33" facs="tcp:170270:26"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="34" facs="tcp:170270:27"/>leave theſe men to theſe na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked Ordinances. The poore man that lay at the poole of <hi>Betheſda,</hi> lay there long, and longer he might have layne, if Jeſus Chriſt had not come and given cure to him. There are three things in Ordinances when they become effectuall, there's a Majeſty, a ſweetneſs, and a power.</p>
               <p>Firſt,
<note place="margin">There is a Majeſty and glory in Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances.</note> A Majeſty and a glory diſcovered 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3. laſt, <hi>We all with open face behold as in a glaſs the glory of the Lord, are changed into the ſame image, &amp;c.</hi> What's that? The glaſſe is Goſpell-Ordinances, they are the win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dowes by which we looke into the glory of God: Alaſs, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out this, Preaching is but bab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, Praying is but howling. It's not the Ordinances that puts a glory upon God, but
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:170270:27"/>it's God that puts a glory up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on Ordinances: what's that that puts a beauty and glory upon all the Ordinances of God? 'tis the preſence of God, the very preſence of God makes all glorious in heaven, and the very preſence of God makes all glorious in the Church; <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>Jehovah Shammah, the Lord is there</hi> is the glory of all Ordinances: yet if you have not God in them, you may ſay as ſhe ſaid, <hi>the glory is departed,</hi> they are but like the beames that are cut off from the Sun, if God be not in them; thus there is a Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty and a glory diſcovered.</p>
               <p>Secondly,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> There's a ſweet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe that the Soule taſts in Ordinances, but when the Soule wants the preſence of God in Ordinances, then there
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:170270:28"/>is no ſweetneſſe in them, for Ordinances to the Soule, when the preſence of God is depar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted from them, carry no more taſt nor ſweetneſſe in them, then is in the white of an egge. The word is ſweeter then the hony and the hony combe when God is in it: what is that that gives a Soule to taſt any ſweetneſſe in any Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance? you may finde it, <hi>Cant.</hi> 2.3. <hi>I ſate under his ſhadow with great delight, and his fruit was ſweet unto my taſt.</hi> (The word is very ſignificant, for it im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porteth ſweetneſſe, or all kind of ſweetneſſe; his fruit was <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>mamtakkim,</hi> all ſweet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe.) Whats the ground that men grow weary of Ordinan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces? 'tis becauſe they taſt no ſweetneſſe in them? what's the ground they taſt no ſweet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:170270:28"/>in them? 'tis becauſe God is withdrawne from them.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Thirdly, there muſt not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly bee a Majeſty and a glory diſcovered, and ſweetneſs ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted, but there muſt be a pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er felt if ever Ordinances doe you any good, <hi>Iſaiah</hi> 55.1. <hi>Who hath beleeved our report?</hi> why? they had made reports to be beleeved, but none had beleeved the reports that were made; many hearers but few beleevers; 'its ſpoken by way of complaint<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> who hath belee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved our report? why? what's the ground that the report is not beleeved? <hi>To whom is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>he Arme of the Lord revealed?</hi> If the Arme of God be not revealed, no reports of God wil be belee<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ved. <hi>I am not aſhamed of the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell of Chriſt</hi> ſaith the Apoſtle
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:170270:29"/>
                  <hi>Paul,</hi> why? <hi>it's the power of God to Salvation.</hi> So the <hi>weapons of our warfare are not carnall but mighty;</hi> mighty, how? through God, for the bringing downe of every luſt that exalts its ſelf againſt him: If God bee not in an Ordinance, an Ordinance is of no effect. The</p>
               <p n="2">
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Poſi. </seg>2</label> 2. Poſition, That when Communion with God ſhall be perfected and compleated, then all Ordinances ſhall bee aboliſhed and removed, Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances ſhall be continued, till our Communion be perfected, till we all come <hi>in the unity of the faith, and of the knowledge of the Son of God to a perfect man, unto the meaſure of the ſtature of the fulneſſe of Chriſt. Epheſ.</hi> 4.13. When once wee are brought to a perfect man in Chriſt Jeſus, then, and not till then,
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:170270:29"/>ſhall all Ordinances bee taken from us. In the ſtate of our perfection God will do theſe two things: Firſt, hee will ſucceede all Ordinances; Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly, hee will exceede all Ordinances, all our vailes ſhall then be taken away, when we come to look God in the face, <hi>Cant.</hi> 2.17. <hi>Vntill the day breake, and the ſhadows flee away, turne beloved, and be thou like a Roe, or a young Hart upon the mountaines of Bether.</hi> Some ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pound it of the night of trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles, and of miſeries that the Church of God lay under; others of the obſcurity and darkeneſſe that was upon them: others of thoſe cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies and ſhadowes that they could not ſee through; others of the comming of the Lord Jeſus Chriſt as the Sun
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:170270:30"/>in to the world to make day, untill the day breake; others of Chriſts laſt appearance re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moving all clouds and vailes, and cauſing the day to breake forth, &amp; the ſhadow to fly a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way; untill the day breakes forth, the ſhadow nere flies a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way: when once the Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion of the Saints of God ſhall be perfected, then al Ordinan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces ſhall be removed, the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance ſhall ſucceede and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceede the ſhadowes. Thus Communion with God in Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinances ſhall laſt till Jeſus Chriſt make a ſurrender of his Mediatoriall Kingdome, when Jeſus Chriſt ſhall give up his kingdome to his Father, and all the Saints shall be perfect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, then their Communion with God through Mediums shall be done away. The</p>
               <pb n="41" facs="tcp:170270:30"/>
               <p n="3">
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Poſit. </seg>3</label> 3. Poſition: The more ſpirituall and pure any Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances are, the more Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion the Saints of God have with God in them. Under the Law when they lay under more carnall Adminiſtrati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons &amp; Ordinances, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, <hi>Heb.</hi> 9.10. They are cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led <hi>carnall Ordinances,</hi> for the moſt part they had but tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſient, not conſtant acts of Communion with God, and theſe acts of Communion they had but ſeldome, compar'd with thoſe acts of Communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on that the Saints have under the Goſpell. Now, as the Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinances grow up in purity and perfection, ſo should wee grow up in Communion with God in them: for the more ſpirituall the Ordinances are, the more there is of theſe three
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:170270:31"/>things in them. 1. There's the more of the nature of God in them. 2. There's the more of the preſence of God with them. 3. There's the more of the bleſſing of God upon them. The ground of Gods withdrawing and departing from Ordinances hath beene mens intolerable corrupting and defiling of them, ſo that hee would neither owne the worſhip, nor the worſhippers at all, <hi>Rev.</hi> 2.1. <hi>who walketh in the midſt of the ſeven golden Candlesticks:</hi> If the Candle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſticks be gold, and there be no droſſe in them, then he will walk in the midſt of them; but if they be droſſie, and not golden Candleſticks, God takes no delight to walk among ſuch, <hi>Cant.</hi> 2.16. <hi>My beloved feeds among the Lillies;</hi>
                  <pb n="43" facs="tcp:170270:31"/>It is not ſaid he feeds among <hi>Thornes,</hi> but hee feeds among the <hi>Lillies.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But for the further clearing of the Saints Communion with God; I ſhall do theſe four things.</p>
               <list>
                  <item>1. Give you the grounds, of all the fellowſhip and the Communion that the Saints have with God in Ordinances.</item>
                  <item>2. Shew you the properties of this Communion.</item>
                  <item>3. The ſeverall Acts of Communion.</item>
                  <item>4. Thoſe glorious ends that God aimed at in the gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving forth Communion unto the Saints in Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinances.</item>
               </list>
               <p>But before I enter upon theſe, I muſt promiſe ſome few particulars.</p>
               <pb n="44" facs="tcp:170270:32"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Object.</hi> It will be ſaid, God is in Heaven, and the Saints are upon the Earth, God is a conſuming fire, and wee are but as withered ſtubble, how ſhall we draw near unto God, or appear before him?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> There are two ſorts of perſons in the world, Firſt, Sinners, Secondly, Saints; un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>regenerate men, and regene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate men, and they are both called upon to draw nigh to God. <hi>Jam.</hi> 4.8. <hi>Draw nigh to God, and he will draw nigh to you: clenſe your hands ye Sinners, and purifie your hearts yee double minded: obſerve thoſe three tings.</hi>
               </p>
               <list>
                  <item>1. Here's a duty injoined; drawing nigh to God.</item>
                  <item>2. A bleſſing promiſed; hee will draw nigh to you.</item>
                  <pb n="45" facs="tcp:170270:32"/>
                  <item>3. There is a threefold du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plicity mentioned, ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners and double-mind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, cleanſe and purifie, hands and heart.</item>
               </list>
               <p>The firſt ſhewes the perſons to whom the duty is in joined to draw near to God; <hi>Liz.</hi> Sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners and double minded; the other two points are the way and means by which the du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty enjoined, may be rightly ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compliſhed, <hi>viz.</hi> by cleanſing and purifying our hearts and hands.</p>
               <p>But it is to be marked that there is twofold drawing nigh to God.</p>
               <list>
                  <item>1. In point of Converſion.</item>
                  <item>2. In point of Communion.</item>
               </list>
               <p>So that you that enjoy Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinances, and are not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verted, you can have no Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion with God in Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances.
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:170270:33"/>And for the proof of this, that ungenerate men can have no Communion with God in Ordinances, will appear by theſe Arguments.</p>
               <p n="1">
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Argu. </seg>1</label> 1. Becauſe there muſt be a State of Communion, before ever there can bee any acts of Communion; There muſt bee a ſtate of Marriage before ever there be a performance of the acts of the married; you muſt be made neere before you can draw neere, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 2.13. <hi>Ye who were ſometimes afarr off are made nigh by the blood of Jeſus:</hi> when once a ſoule is made nigh, then it can draw nigh. The Prodigall Son when hee is returned home to the houſe of his Father, and made nigh to him, then the Father <hi>kiſſes him and embraces him, Luk.</hi> 15.20. love is very quick ſighted,
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:170270:33"/>he ſaw him; &amp; 'tis very tender hearted, he had compaſſion upon him, &amp; fell upo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> his neck, and kiſſed him: will you ſee what a man is in his naturall eſtate, which clearly ſpeaks he hath no communion with God, <hi>Eph.</hi> 2.12. <hi>That at that time ye were without Chriſt, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing aliens from the common-wealth of Iſrael, and ſtrangers from the covenants of promiſe, having no hope, and without God in the world.</hi> There are five withouts, without Chriſt, without the Church, without the promiſe, without hope, without God in the world. Can two walke together except they bee a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greed? God and a ſinner are not agreed, there's no walking together therefore. A man muſt be made a free man be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he can trade as a freeman;
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:170270:34"/>ſo before you can have any in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tercourſe with heaven, or any free trading there, you muſt bee made free of the city a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove.</p>
               <p n="2">
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Poſit. </seg>2</label> 2. An unregenerate man can have no Communion with God in Ordinances, becauſe hee doth not live the ſame kind of life that God lives; No Creature can have any fellowſhip or Communion with God, but he that lives the ſame kind of life with God; A man cannot have Communion with Beaſts, why? becauſe they do not live a Rationall life, <hi>Eph.</hi> 4.18. <hi>having their underſtandings darkned, being alienated from the life of God.</hi> No things have any Communion, but onely thoſe that live the ſame kind of life with that with which they
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:170270:34"/>have Communion: a Saint lives the ſame kind of life with God, though he hath not the ſame degree of life with God.</p>
               <p n="3">
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Argu∣ment. </seg>3</label> 3. Argument: An unregene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate man can have no fellow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip with God in Ordinances, becauſe he is ſwallowed up with other fellowſhip, and with other Communions: there is a fivefold fellowſhip and Communion that an un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>regenerate man hath, that makes him he can have no Communion with God.</p>
               <p n="1">1. He takes up his fellow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip and Communion with ſin; ſin is the onely Jewel that he wears in his boſom, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6.15, 16. <hi>what fellowſhip hath Chriſt with</hi> Belial, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.7. <hi>The carnall mind is enmity a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst God;</hi> Enmity 'tis the
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:170270:35"/>higheſt degree of hatred, 'tis the affection ſet on edge a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt God; an Enemy may be reconciled, but enmity muſt be deſtroyed; what fellowſhip can they have with the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of lights, whoſe fellow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip is taken up with the works of darkneſs?</p>
               <p n="2">2. They are ſwallowed up with the fellowſhip and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion with ſinners; thoſe that are Gods profeſſed E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemies, are their boſom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>friends, the darling delights of their Souls are in the So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciety of thoſe in whom God takes no pleaſure, nor no de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light.</p>
               <p n="3">3. They take up their fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowſhip and Communion with this world, <hi>James</hi> 4.4. <hi>know ye not that the friendſhip of the world is enmity with God,</hi>
                  <pb n="51" facs="tcp:170270:35"/>whoſoever therefore will be a friend of the world, is the Enemy of God: they make up their Heaven upon Earth: there are three things where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in they go out to the world.</p>
               <list>
                  <item>1. They let out their choi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſt love.</item>
                  <item>2. They lay out their choi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſt paines.</item>
               </list>
               <p n="3">3. They Anchor their great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt hopes upon the world: Now thoſe that are taken up with the fellowſhip and Communion with this world, at what a diſtance do they ſtand from Communion and fellowſhip with God? Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures hath their hearts, God hath them not.</p>
               <p n="4">4. They are ſwallowed up in Communion and fellow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip with falſe foundations:
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:170270:36"/>this is a certain rule, that look whatſoever the foundation is that we build our ſouls up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, that's it with which wee have Communion, <hi>Job</hi> 8.14, 15. <hi>He ſhall lean upon his houſe, but it ſhall not ſtand,</hi> &amp;c. Thoſe hopes that it hath, that it ſhal go well with him to all Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity, theſe are called his houſe, he reſts upon them, and hee hath Communion with them. Houſes,
<list>
                     <item>1. They are dwelling pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, a man lives in his houſe.</item>
                     <item>2. They are hiding places, in the time of a ſtorm men retire to their houſes for ſhelter.</item>
                     <item>3. They are reſting pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces.</item>
                  </list>
               </p>
               <p n="4">4. They are places that when once they are built,
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:170270:36"/>men will keep them if they can from falling down; Now ſinners are ſwallowed up in Communion and fellowship with thoſe falſe bottomed hopes that they have laid their ſoules upon, they reſt in thoſe houſes that they make to themſelves, though their hopes bee but like Spiders webs, yet they lean upon their houſes.</p>
               <p n="5">5. They are ſwallowed up in fellowship and Communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on with the very Devil him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, 1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 5.19. <hi>we know that we are of God, and that the whole world lies in wickedneſs;</hi> In the <hi>Greek</hi> 'tis thus, and the whole world lies in that wicked one, the Devil, and they maintain Communion together, the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil ſpirits haunt their Spirits. The Devil in Scripture is ſaid
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:170270:37"/>to have all thoſe Acts of wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip performed to him by ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, that Chriſt is ſaid to have performed to him by Saints: hath Jeſus Chriſt his Miniſters? the Devil hath his Miniſters alſo; Miniſters of Satan transforming them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves into Angels of light: hath Chriſt his Churches? ſo hath the Devil, which is call-the Synagogue of Sathan: hath Chriſt his Ordinances and Altars? ſo hath the Devil too, he hath his Table, and his Communicants; you cannot bee partakers of the Lords Table, and the Table of Devils.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Argu. </seg>4</label> The fourth Argument to prove that unregenerate men can have no fellowship and Communion with God in Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinances; becauſe they live
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:170270:37"/>under a Legal Covenant: E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vangelical Communion is not bottomed upon Legal Covenants. In Converſion there is a double change.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="55-105" type="pages">
               <p n="1">1. A change of a mans na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, and that is wrought within him.</p>
               <p n="2">2. A change of a mans ſtate, and that is wrought upon him.</p>
               <p>Every unregenerate man is under the firſt Covenant, which admits of no Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion with God ſince it is bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken. There are five things wee loſt in our fall;
<list>
                     <item>1. Our holy Image, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came vile; hence</item>
                     <item>2. Our Son-ſhip, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came ſlaves.</item>
                     <item>3. Our friendſhip, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came Enemies.</item>
                     <item>4. Our Communion, and
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:170270:38"/>became ſtrangers.</item>
                     <item>5. Our glory, and became miſerable.</item>
                  </list>
               </p>
               <p>Now 'tis impoſſible till ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners be tranſlated from a bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken Covenant of works that was made with them in <hi>Adam,</hi> to a Covenant of grace that is made in Chriſt, that ever they ſhould come up to Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion with God: you muſt know this, that Communion with God is no Legal diſpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſation, and therefore every perſon that is duly under the Law, cannot enjoy Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion with God.</p>
               <p>Having premiſed theſe, I come to thoſe four partioulars I laid down, <hi>viz.</hi> to give you the grounds, the properties, the Acts, and the ends of the Communion.</p>
               <p>Firſt, For the Grounds of all
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:170270:38"/>the fellowſhip and Communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on that the Saints have with God in Ordinances and they are five; for this Communion ariſeth,
<list>
                     <item>1. From his electing love.</item>
                     <item>2. From the Covenant-ſtate wherein believers ſtand.</item>
                     <item>3. From our union with Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt.</item>
                     <item>4. From our Intereſt in the Spirit.</item>
                     <item>5. Our conformity to the Lord Jeſus Chriſt.</item>
                  </list>
               </p>
               <p n="1">
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Ground. </seg>1</label> I. Ground of our Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion with God is his Electing love, that's the foundati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of all our bleſſedneſſe, and the onely ſpring of all our mercies which without Gods Electing love, no mercy would be a mercy to us, and with it no miſery will make us miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable; The Lord hath choſen
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:170270:39"/>you unto three great ends, in ſubordination one to the other; he hath choſen you to ſalvation, to reconciliation, and to communion, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 4.3. <hi>The Lord hath ſet apart him that is godly for himſelfe.</hi> God hath picked and culled every Godly man out of the world, and ſet him aſide; For what? for himſelfe; for himſelfe, what's that? It doth not only note for ſpirituall ſervice, but for the higheſt priviled<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges: he hath ſet the godly man apart for theſe two ends: Firſt, for the enjoyment of communion with him on earth: Secondly, for the fru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ition of bleſſedneſſe with him in heaven. The Lord hath ſet, &amp;c.</p>
               <list>
                  <item>1. Conſider who is it that hath done it? It's
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:170270:39"/>God that hath <hi>ſet him a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>2. What hath he done? He hath ſet him apart, put him diſtinct from all the world.</item>
                  <item>3. Who is it that is thus ſet apart? It is the <hi>man that is godly.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>4. What is the end of this action, for which this man is ſet apart? He is ſet apart for God.</item>
               </list>
               <p>'Tis the choyceſt duty that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longs to us to ſet our ſelves apart for God; and 'tis one of the choiceſt mercies of God, to ſet us apart for himſelfe. The Lord doth ſeparate to himſelfe for imployment, and for fellowſhip; he will em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ploy that man, and he will have communion with that man. The Angels, they are of
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:170270:40"/>all creatures taken to ſpeciall communion with God, they behold the face of God the Father which is in Heaven. It was excellently expreſſed by <hi>Tertullian,</hi> the Saints in this life are the men that are the Lords attendants, ſetting the Lord alwaies before them, and ſtanding alwaies before him, waiting upon him. <hi>Zech.</hi> 3.7. <hi>Thus ſaith the Lord, if thou wilt walk in my waies,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>I will give thee</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>mah-lechim, Walks:</hi> that is, <hi>places to walk:</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>en hagnome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dim ha-elleh, inter ſtantes illos,</hi> among theſe that ſtand by: Who be they? The meaning is conceived to be this; the Angels, they alwaies ſtand before God, thouſand thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſands compaſſe his Throne; now when the Lord ſpeaks
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:170270:40"/>of taking a people into inti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mate familiarity with him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, he ſaith, he will give them walkes, or Galleries to walk in among the Angels themſelves, to attend upon him, and hence are thoſe and ſuch like expreſſions of this their office and duty: <hi>I have ſet the Lord alwaies before me,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>and as the eyes of Servants are upon the hands of their Maſters, and as the eyes of a waiting-Maid unto the hand of her Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſſe; ſo our eyes are upon the Lord our God, (waiting) till he have mercy upon us,</hi> &amp;c. Now had the Lord choſen you but to Salvation, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he did leave the Angels to fall under the curſe of their covenant bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken, this had been a great mercy; but this will not ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfie electing love, only to
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:170270:41"/>make up old breaches, and then to ſhut up its boſome: or to ſay to us, as <hi>David</hi> ſaid to <hi>Abſolon,</hi> let him return to his houſe, but let him never ſee my face; no, but God will have his children look him in the face: therefore in the <hi>Luke</hi> 214. there is not only <hi>glory to God in the higheſt, and peace on earth,</hi> which is recon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciliation, but there is <hi>good will towards men:</hi> There is fellow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip and communion, peace will not ſerve loves turn, but there muſt be good will too. The love of God did not only ordain us to friendſhip, but it did ordain us to fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowſhip. The Father in love came forth from all eternity to us, that we to all eternity might enjoy communion with him: I had almoſt ſaid
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:170270:41"/>that the very eſſence of the love of God, and all the a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctings of it, lead to commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion and fellowſhip with him.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Ground. </seg>2</label> The ſecond ground of communion is from the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant of Grace under which you ſtand. When <hi>Adam</hi> had ſinned, he ranne away from God; when he made himſelfe a ſinner, God made him an exile: Now in the Covenant under which <hi>Adam</hi> was, he had communion with God as a Creature with his Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor, but not as a child with his Father. Now the Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant of grace, it is a conjugall Covenant; and conjugall Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venants are all of them made for the enjoying of commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion, <hi>Hoſea</hi> 2.19. <hi>I will be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troth thee to me for ever; yea,
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:170270:42"/>I will betroth thee unto me in righteouſneſſe, and in judgment, and in loving kindneſſe, and in mercies:</hi> Mark, there are foure things in theſe words, that point out the firmneſſe, and the ſtability of our Marriages with Chriſt: Firſt, 'tis done in righteouſneſſe; Secondly, in judgment; Thirdly, in lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving kindneſſe; Fourthly, in tender mercies: Now what are the fruits and effects of this ſame conjugall relation, and of our joyning to Chriſt? See <hi>Chap.</hi> 3.3. <hi>And I ſaid, thou ſhalt be for me many daies, and ſhalt not be for another, ſo will I be for thee.</hi> Chriſt promiſeth to be for the Saints, and he engageth the Saints to be for him, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 2.12. <hi>Strangers to the Covenants of promiſe, without God, and without hope in the
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:170270:42"/>world;</hi> Till ſuch time as a man be brought into Covenant with God, he is a ſtranger to God, and therefore hath no communion with him; he ſtands at the greateſt diſtance from this fellowſhip with the Father, and with his ſonne Jeſus Chriſt. But now, when a man is brought within the verge of the Covenant of grace, then hath he commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion in all the grace of the Covenant. The Covenant of Grace hath two properties peculiar to it, which were not in the firſt Covenant: Firſt, there is <hi>Foedus Amicitiae,</hi> and <hi>Paedus Conjugale;</hi> a Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant of friendſhip, and a Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jugal Covenant. This is the great end of the Goſpell, <hi>Luke</hi> 2.14. the Angels de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed the purpoſe of God,
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:170270:43"/>and what is it? <hi>to give peace on earth, and good will:</hi> God contents himſelfe not only with peace, but good will; not only reconciliation, but communion: and the Lord delights his people ſhould come to him in a familiar way, under tearms of inti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>macy, <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 2.16. a ſtrange expreſſion, <hi>Thou ſhalt not call me</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>Iſhi, (ſaith the Lord) and ſhalt call me no more</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>Baali: Baali</hi> ſignifies my Lord; God would be called by Lord no more; but call me <hi>Iſhi,</hi> what's that? my Hus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Ground </seg>3</label> The third ground of com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion of Saints with God is, their union with Jeſus Chriſt. Anſwerable to your union, there will be your communion. There's a five<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fold union.</p>
               <pb n="67" facs="tcp:170270:43"/>
               <list>
                  <item>1. An union Politicall, as between a King and his people.</item>
                  <item>2. An union naturall, as between head and mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers.</item>
                  <item>3. An union ſinfull, as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt one ſinner and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother.</item>
                  <item>4. An union Hypoſtaticall, between the two natures of Chriſt.</item>
                  <item>5. An union myſticall, and that is between Chriſt and the Saints.</item>
               </list>
               <p>Look what Righteouſneſſe Chriſt as Mediator hath, is yours; and the communion that Chriſt hath with the Father, we have intereſt in it alſo, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12.12. <hi>For as the body is one, and hath many mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers, and all the memes of that one body being many, are one bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy,
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:170270:44"/>ſo alſo is Chriſt.</hi> God the Father never looks on Chriſt and the Saints as two, but as one. Will you take a view of Chriſts communion with the Father, <hi>Dan.</hi> 7.13. <hi>I ſaw, and behold one like the Son of man came with the clouds of heaven, and came to the Antient of daies, and they brought him neer before him.</hi> 1 <hi>John</hi> 18. <hi>He lives in the boſome of the Father.</hi> The boſome 'tis the ſeat of ſecrets of love, and of fellowſhip.</p>
               <p>Now in this his commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion with the Father, we are in no leſſe then the whole of our Salvation intereſſed; for he is brought before the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſtanding at his right hand, and lying in his boſom, not only to enjoy communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on with his Father himſelfe, but to intercede for our com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:170270:44"/>with him alſo.</p>
               <p>Union that diſpoſeth for communion. There can be no communion where there is no union, <hi>Rev.</hi> 3.20. <hi>Behold I ſtand at the dore and knock, if any man hear my voice, and open the dore, I will come in to him, and will ſup with him, and he with me.</hi> Firſt, there muſt be opening of the dore, and Jeſus Chriſt muſt come in, before ever there be ſupping together: none of the fare that is to feaſt a Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an comes, till Chriſt him ſelf brings it: If the dore be ſhut againſt Chriſts perſon, then there is a Baracado to all com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion. <hi>Cant.</hi> 5.5. <hi>I am come into my Garden, my ſister, my ſpouſe, &amp;c.</hi> And then, <hi>Eat O friends, drink, yea, drink abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dantly, O beloved.</hi> There are two things that we enjoy by
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:170270:45"/>vertue of our union with Chriſt. Firſt, ſatisfaction in him. Secondly, Communion and fellowship with him. Look what fellowship and Communion Chriſt hath with the Father, it is by ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue of his union with him, and look what fellowship and Communion wee have with Chriſt, 'tis by vertue of our union with him, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.22.23. mark how the Relation there riſeth, <hi>All are yours;</hi> how comes that? <hi>ye are Chriſts, and Chriſt is Gods:</hi> and <hi>Rom.</hi> 5.2. <hi>by whom wee have acceſſe into this grace wherein we ſtand:</hi> note this;
<list>
                     <item>1. Believers have under the Goſpel acceſſe into glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious grace; <hi>into this grace.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>2. That the meritorious
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:170270:45"/>cauſe of believers acceſſe into this grace is the Lord Jeſus Chriſt; <hi>by whom.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>3. The ſame ſtate of grace to which the Goſpel brings us, in that eſtate doth Chriſt keep us; <hi>wherein we ſtand.</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </p>
               <p n="4">4. That a Saint through the ſight of his acceſſe to, and his ſtanding in this grace, is made to rejoice in hope of the glory of God, as is ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed in the words follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing; for the clearing and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmation of the ſubſtance of all thoſe four particulars, <hi>viz. that believers</hi> have acceſſe un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to, and are kept into that ſtate of grace wherein they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyce and glory, onely by Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt and his mediation there is a remarkable expreſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:170270:46"/>of the Apoſtle, in <hi>Eph.</hi> 2.13. <hi>but now in Chriſt Jeſus, yee who ſometimes were far off, are made nigh by the blood of Jeſus; for he is our peace, who hath made both one, and hath broken down the middle wall of partition:</hi> Thoſe who are without Chriſt, are afar off three man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of waies:
<list>
                     <item>1. In point of opinion and apprehenſion.</item>
                     <item>2. In point of fellowſhip and Communion.</item>
                     <item>3. In point of grace and converſion.</item>
                  </list>
               </p>
               <p>Now as <hi>Joſeph</hi> ſaid to his Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren, <hi>bring your Brother</hi> Benja<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>min <hi>with you, or elſe ſee not my face any more;</hi> So doth God ſay to ſinners when they come nigh to enjoy communion with him, <hi>bring Jeſus Chriſt in your arms, or elſe never look me in the
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:170270:46"/>face.</hi> It's the cuſtom of ſome Countries and foraign Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, that when ever they ſpeak any thing to the King, they take up his Son in their armes; ſure I am 'tis the cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtom of Heaven, that who ever ſhall have Communion with God and enjoy fellowſhip with his ſpirit, they muſt take his Son in their armes, and carry Chriſt along with them. <hi>Heb.</hi> 4.16. <hi>Let us therefore come boldly to the Throne of grace, that we may obtain mercy, and find grace to help in time of need.</hi> God hath ſet up a Throne, and that Thone that he hath ſet up is a gratious Throne; and 'tis ſet up for poor ſinners, and for poor ſinners to come freely and boldly too; to take liberty in ſpeaking to God: it's ſet up for theſe two ends, for
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:170270:47"/>the obtaining of mercy, and for the finding of grace that may help us in time of need; that is, for the finding of fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour, and fellowſhip with God. And it is upon the alone account of the Lord Jeſus Chriſt, that we can come with boldneſſe to it. Look on the words foregoing, <hi>verſe</hi> 15: <hi>For we have not an high Prieſt, that cannot be touched with the feeling of our infirmities, &amp;c. Let us there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore come boldly, &amp;c. John</hi> 14.6. <hi>I am the way, the truth, and the life,</hi> there is no comming to the Father, but by Jeſus Chriſt: and <hi>Heb.</hi> 10.19. <hi>Having therefore brethren, boldneſſe to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter into the holiest by the blood of Jeſus.</hi> The ſinfulleſt wretches in the world, if they be brought into Jeſus Chriſt, may come boldly, and have
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:170270:47"/>communion with God the Father, <hi>Cant.</hi> 1.4. <hi>The King hath brought me into his Cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers.</hi> There is no going into the chambers, the places of communion with God the Father, but by being led by the hand of the King of Saints, the Lord Jeſus Chriſt thi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Ground. </seg>4</label> The fourth ground of our communion with God, is the Spirit of Chriſt in us; this is one of the main ends why believers receive the Spirit of Chriſt; the Spirit of Chriſt is not only received as a bond of union, but as a means of communion, the Spirit of Chriſt in believers hath theſe foure things in it.</p>
               <pb n="76" facs="tcp:170270:48"/>
               <list>
                  <item>1 It's a Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of Union.</item>
                  <item>2 It's a Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of Unction.</item>
                  <item>3 It's a Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of Action.</item>
                  <item>4 It's a Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of Fellowſhip.</item>
               </list>
               <p>As</p>
               <p n="1">1. It's a ſpirit of Union, Its that which is the everlaſting tie of the God head in it ſelfe, the ſpirit running forth through the Father, and the Son; or proceeding from the Father and the Son, as it is ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed in the Goſpell; ſo 'tis that which is the very tie and knot of the Saints and Chriſt, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6.17. <hi>Hee that is joyned to the Lord is one Spirit.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. It's a Spirit of Union, 1 <hi>John</hi> 2.27. <hi>but the anointing which ye have received abideth in you, &amp;c.</hi> The oyntment that was powred upon the head of <hi>Aaron</hi> it ran downe to the skirts of all his Garment; the
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:170270:48"/>ſpirit of God like to oyntment that was powred forth upon the head of Chriſt, and it doth run downe to all his mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers.</p>
               <p n="3">3. It's a Spirit of Action, ſaith the Apoſtle; <hi>If ye through the Spirit mortifie the deeds of the fleſh.</hi> The ſpirit is the power<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulleſt weapon in our hands to put fleſh to death in us; it is not an idle, but an active ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit.</p>
               <p n="4">4. It's a ſpirit of fellowſhip and Communion, <hi>Eph.</hi> 2.18: <hi>For through him we both have an acceſſe by one ſpirit, unto the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,</hi> we both have acceſſe; that is, Jew and Gentile; though they are two Nations, that one ſpirit leades them both to the Father; The Spirit of Chriſt is not onely a ſpirit of manifeſtation and of revela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion;
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:170270:49"/>but it is a ſpirit of Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plication and of Manuducti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, It leads us by the hand to the Father, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.14. <hi>As many as are led by the Spirit of God, they the Sons of God.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Thus you ſee that intimacy is grounded upon your Union with Chriſt. The ground of all Communion is Union, now anſwerable to the Union ſuch muſt the Communion be, if the Union bee very neere, truly then the Communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on muſt bee very intimate, <hi>Epheſians</hi> 5.3. <hi>Wee are of his fleſh and of his bone,</hi> it is ſo neere; nay neerer, <hi>hee that is joyned to the Lord is one Spirit,</hi> what's the end why the Lord hath made ſo neere a Union? truly it is that there may bee an intimate Communion an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwerable, he is in us like lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven,
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:170270:49"/>even as the leaven incor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porates it ſelfe, that there can bee no ſeparation between it and the dough. One end of the Hypoſtaticall Union was the myſticall Union, Chriſt takes the two natures into one perſon, that ſo you might be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come one with him Conſider, there is a morall union that is made by love, for love is <hi>Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectus unionis,</hi> an uniting affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, ſuch a union the Angells have, and <hi>Adam</hi> had in the ſtate of Innocency; I but there is likewiſe an union that faith makes, a myſticall union, that is another kind of union then ever the Angells had, or can have; The Angells are never ſaid to bee the brethren of Chriſt, and the members of Chriſt, Chriſt is ſaid to be their head, but they are never ſaid
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:170270:50"/>to be his members; there is ſome thing morein that myſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call union which is by faith between Chriſt and beleevers; then there can be in that uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on which is between Chriſt and the Angells. Now if the end of union be Communion, why hath the Lord made ſo neere a union, but for an inti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mate familiarity and commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Ground. </seg>5</label> The fift ground of Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion is our conformity and ſimilitude to Jeſus Chriſt, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formity and ſimilitude is the ground of all communion: A Saint being made like unto God receives communion and fellowſhip with God, the more a Chriſtian growes up into a conformity with God, the higher hee growes in his fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowſhip and communion with
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:170270:50"/>God. The leſſe any man hath of a Divine Reſemblance, the leſſe hee enjoyes of a Divine Communion; When our I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mages ſhall be perfected, then our communion ſhall be com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleated: the more imperfect our Image is, the more imper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect our Communion is.</p>
               <p>I ſhall lay downe two pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſitions.</p>
               <list>
                  <item>1. That a Saint hath a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formitie, and a reſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blance of God upon him.</item>
                  <item>2. That his conformitie and reſemblance to God, is the ground of his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion with God.</item>
               </list>
               <p n="1">1. That a Saint hath a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formity, and a reſemblance of God upon him, 1 <hi>Iohn</hi> 4.17. <hi>For as he is, ſo are we in this world.</hi> And 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.4. <hi>Whereby are given unto us, exceeding
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:170270:51"/>great and pretious promiſes, that by them we may be made partakers of the Divine Nature.</hi> There's a kind of impreſſion of the glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious attributes of God in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtampt upon every Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an.</p>
               <p n="1">1. There's a kind of Omni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>potency, <hi>Phil.</hi> 4.13. <hi>I can do all things through Chriſt, that streng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thens me.</hi> What can Omnipo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tency do more then all things? and yet <hi>Paul</hi> can do no leſſe, by the ſtrength he receives from Chriſt.</p>
               <p n="2">2. There's a kind of Omni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciency in all the Saints, 1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 2.20. <hi>But ye have an Unction from the holy one, and ye know all things.</hi> There are ſome foot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteps of that glorious Attri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bute of God, that are to be ſeen upon gracious ſoules, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 2.15. <hi>He that is ſpirituall
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:170270:51"/>judgeth all things, yet be himſelfe is judged of no man:</hi> He is the judge of all, and yet none the judge of him.</p>
               <p n="3">3. There are ſome impreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions of the Allſufficiency of God, that is engraven upon a Chriſtian, <hi>Phil.</hi> 4.18. <hi>I have all, and abound, and am full.</hi> So 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6.10. <hi>As having nothing, and yet poſſeſſing all things.</hi> So 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.6. <hi>Godlineſſe, with con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentment is great gain.</hi> The Greek reads it thus, Godlineſs with ſelfe-ſufficiency is great gain. So <hi>Solomon</hi> tells us—that a good man ſhall be ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfied from himſelfe, not from another, but from him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe: There is ſome kind of impreſſion of the All-ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ency of God upon a Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an.</p>
               <p n="4">4. There's a kind of Omni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſence
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:170270:52"/>of God upon a Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian. Heaven and earth are the two great Continents of all things; now a Divine ſoule is travelling in them both at once, <hi>Phil.</hi> 3.12. <hi>Our conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſation is in heaven;</hi> though they themſelves were on earth, yet their converſation was in hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, ſo that they are both in heaven and earth at once: where ever God is, there the Saints are, for they have their dwelling places in him, <hi>Pſalm.</hi> 73.23. <hi>Nevertheleſs I am conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nually with thee, thy right hand upholdeth me.</hi> A Chriſtian runs through all ſtates and things with God himſelfe, he is led by his Fathers hand through every ſtate.</p>
               <p n="5">5. There's a kind of immor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tality put upon a Saint; mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tality is written upon the face
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:170270:52"/>of all things that are below, every thing is liable to the ſtroke of death; yet a Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian, though he die daily, yet lives for ever; though the man die, yet the Saint doth not, grace is never laid in the grave, <hi>John</hi> 11.26. <hi>He that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieveth in me ſhall never die:</hi> that is, he ſhall never live un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comfortable, for an uncomfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table life is equivalent to death; and he ſhall never dye eternally, he that believes in me, the ſecond death hath no power over him; he may dy as a man, but he ſhall never dy as a believing man.</p>
               <p n="6">6. There's a kind of immu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tability and unchangableneſſe upon a Chriſtian: In regard of his ſtate he is immutable, he can never change, though in regard of the degrees of his
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:170270:53"/>ſtate he is changing dayly: look what now he is as a Saint, that he ſhall for ever be, he ſhall never loſe the graces that he hath received, for the gifts and callings of God are with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out Repentance; that is, he never repents, nor exerciſeth any acts of ſorrow, for the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtowing of grace upon any of his people. A believer lives unchangably in the midſt of changes, he lives peaceably in the midſt of troubles, and cheerfully in the midſt of wants. Thus you ſee that a Saint hath a conformity, and a reſemblance of God upon him.</p>
               <p>The ſecond Poſition I laid down, that this conformitie is the ground of communion: the more likeneſſe there is in any creature one to another,
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:170270:53"/>the more love, and the more love, the more deſire of com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion; Birds of a feather will flock together: Things that carry a contrariety can never admit of any commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity: what communion hath light and darkneſſe together, which are ſo oppoſite to each other? The light expells the darkneſſe, and the darkneſſe drawes a ſhaddow over the light. The Holy Ghoſt tells us in plain language, that light hath fellowſhip with nothing but light, and darkneſſe hath fellowſhip with nothing but darkneſſe, 1 <hi>John</hi> 1.6, 7. <hi>If we ſay that we have fellowſhip with him and walk in darkneſs, we lie, and do not the truth: But if we walk in the light, as hee is in the light, we have fellowſhip one with another, and the blood of
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:170270:54"/>Jeſus Christ his Son clenſeth us from all ſinne.</hi> There can bee no communion with Chriſt, except there be a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formitie to Chriſt. Now many Soules are there that delude and deceive themſelves, and thinke they have communion when they have none; but a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſſe, if you be not made like unto Chriſt, you can ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver have communion with Chriſt in grace, nor communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on with Chriſt in glory.</p>
               <p>Thus you ſee this Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion ariſeth from the confor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity that is in the Saints un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Chriſt: likenes is the ground of love, and ſuitableneſſe is the ground of intimacy; that is the reaſon why you ſay a man is knowne by his communion. Princes you judge of their tempers by
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:170270:54"/>their favorites; the reaſon is, becauſe a mans Spirit never cloſethin intimat ſociety with any man, but one that hath a ſutableneſſe with himſelfe. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6.17. <hi>There can be no com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion betwixt light and darke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, Chriſt and Belial;</hi> where there is no conformity, there is no communion, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.29. what is the great end you aime at? to bee like unto his Son. So then, when your conformi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty ſhall bee perfect, then your communion ſhall be ſwallow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed up in viſion, for viſion is but union perfect.</p>
               <p>Secondly, To give you the Properties of this communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and they are theſe ſixe.</p>
               <pb n="88" facs="tcp:170270:55"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="89" facs="tcp:170270:55"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="90" facs="tcp:170270:56"/>
               <p>
                  <list>
                     <item>1. Tis a <hi>Superla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive,</hi> and tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cendent</item>
                     <item>2. A free and vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luntary</item>
                     <item>3. A cloſe and neare</item>
                     <item>4. A growing and encreaſing</item>
                     <item>5. A Spirituall &amp; Supernaturall</item>
                     <item>6. A delightfull and compla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>centiall</item>
                  </list> Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</p>
               <p n="1">1. 'Tis a Superlative and a tranſcendent communion, a communion that is above all communions, it excells all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther communions and fellow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhips in the inferior world. There are two very ſad ſights in the world; one is to ſee a bad man inflam'd with joy; the other is to ſee a good man devoured and overwhelmed
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:170270:56"/>with ſorrow. Let me pluck downe the pride of the natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall man, and raiſe up the heart of the ſpirituall man. There be many other communions in the world, but this is above them all, the communion that the Saints have with God compared with other Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munions, 'tis as <hi>Saul</hi> among the people, that was higher by the head and ſhoulders then the reſt of them, 'tis as the Sunne compar'd with the planets far larger, and far more glorious then any one of them, nay then all of them: you that take up the communion without God, below God, beſides God, nay (it may be in ſome things) a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt God; know this, that it is much inferiour to the Communion that the Saints have with God, <hi>Cant.</hi> 1.2. <hi>Let
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:170270:57"/>him kiſſe me with with the kiſſes of his mouth: for thy love is better then wine.</hi> It was the ſaying of a precious Saint, That one houres communion with God was more worth then the whole world; and indeede the Saints are able to ſet to their ſeale that this is true; will you ſee them doing of it, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 84.10. <hi>For a day in thy Court, is better then a thouſand: I had rather bee a doore-keeper in the houſe of God, then to dwell in the tents of wickedneſſe.</hi> One daies communion with God is more worth then all the communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on you have in this world. You that are rocked in the cradle of Creatures, and take the creame of them, that have all the boſoms of created Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellencies to receive from, and to communicate your ſelves
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:170270:57"/>too unto; alas, ther's more ſweetneſſe taſted in the injoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the leaſt part of God, then in the greateſt part of the world. Are not waters much more pleaſant in their ſprings then in their ſtreames? the Saints and people of God they drinke at the fountaines head when they goe to God, and take in all at the firſt hand, the creatures milke out no ſweet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe but when God fills their breſts. The communion that the Saints have with God is Superlative and tranſcendent in a ſix-fold reſpect.</p>
               <p n="1">1. The dignity &amp; excellencie of all communion is according to the perſons with whom we communicate, 1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 1.3. <hi>That which we have ſeene and heard, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare we unto you, that ye alſo may have fellowſhip with us;</hi> why,
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:170270:58"/>with whom is your fellow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip? <hi>Our fellowſhip is with the Father, and with his ſon Jeſus Chriſt.</hi> The fellowſhip that the Saints have, is with all the Perſons in the Trinity. In this communion, there are theſe two things: Firſt, the perſons dignifie the communion: Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly, the communion dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifies the Perſons that enjoyes it: For a Beggar to have com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion with a King, is a very high priviledge; but nothing, compared with the Saints en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joying communion with God. Ordinary communion with extraordinary perſons, raiſeth it to a great height.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Our communion with God muſt needs be a ſuperla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive communion: Why? be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it is the foundation on which all other fellowſhips
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:170270:58"/>are laid. When we brake with God, all creatures brake with us; when man fell from his holineſſe, he fell from his hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſs; when he fell from his Image, he fell from his excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lency. The creatures ſtood upon the ſame termes with us, as we ſtood with God, and by falling from God, all crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures fell from us. There were two things that we loſt in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation to the creature: 1. Our dominion over them; 2. Our communion with them. All men that live in their naturall ſtate have no reall communion with the creature, all creatures are become enemies to them, ſince they themſelves became enemies to God; creatures had no longer their commiſſion to be obedient to us, then we were obedient to God. I but
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:170270:59"/>obſerve now, when once we are reſtored to God, and brought into communion with heaven, all the creatures are reſtored to us, when once we our ſelves are brought to God, <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 2.19. unto 22. <hi>I will betroth thee unto me for ever, &amp;c.</hi> and then, <hi>I will hear the heavens, and the heavens ſhall hear the earth, and the earth ſhall hear the corn, and the wine, and the oyle, and they ſhall hear Jez<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reel.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>There is a five fold com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion, that is bottomed up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on our communion with God.</p>
               <list>
                  <item>1. The communion that the Saints have with the Angels, is all bottomed upon the communion they have with Chriſt.</item>
                  <item>2. The communion that the Saints of God have
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:170270:59"/>one with another; Saints ſhould never have had communion with Saints if they had not had com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion with God 1 <hi>John</hi> 1.3. <hi>Theſe things write wee unto you that ye alſo may have fellowſhip with us; and truly our fellowſhip is with the Father, and with his Son Jeſus Chriſt.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>3. The communion of the Church of the Jewes with the Gentiles, that's laid in their communion with God.</item>
                  <item>4. The communion the glorious Saints have in heaven with the glorious Saints on earth, that's bottomed upon their communion with God, <hi>Heb.</hi> 12.22, 23.</item>
                  <item>5. The communion that we
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:170270:60"/>have with all the crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, that's bottomed upon our communion with Chriſt.</item>
               </list>
               <p n="3">3. This muſt needs bee the moſt ſuperlative communion which is made between God the Father and Jeſus Chriſt, and all the Saints; why? be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe when once it begins, it never ends; perpetuity adds an excellency to it. Things that are evill are much more evill, by how much longer their continuance are; So it is in things that are good, they are much better by their con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuance. Some interpoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons there may bee of a Saints communion ſometimes, but no diſſipation of it: The in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terruptions that the commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion of the Saints meet with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all, are but as clouds before
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:170270:60"/>the Sun, that quickly make their departures again, when it ſhines forth upon them. Other communions often end as ſoone as ever they begin, they are loſt as ſoone as ever they are found, they are taken out of our hands as ſoone as ever they are gotten into our hands; friends quickly die and leave us behind them, or it may bee wee our ſelves dye and leave our friends behinde us, and ſo the knot of com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion is untied; They are not long liv'd that have the longeſt life: But a Saint in communion would never at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine his end, if his communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on ſhould ever come to an end. Such as the foundation is, ſuch is the building that's laid upon it; the foundation of all communion is laid in
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:170270:61"/>love, and love is laid from e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verlaſting to everlaſting; God muſt firſt ceaſe to let out his affections to the Saints, before ever he can ceaſe in commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion with them.</p>
               <p n="4">4. It muſt needs be the higheſt communion, becauſe it is the open dore to all a Saints bleſsedneſſe, ſo you have it in the Text, <hi>I will meet them, and bleſs them:</hi> What a bleſſing did <hi>Jacob</hi> receive, when the Angell wreſtled with him all the night? But <hi>Jacobs</hi> wreſtling goes before his bleſſing: Our communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on makes way for our bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſedneſſe, there are no favours, but come in through the gates of communion.</p>
               <p n="5">5. It muſt needs be the higheſt communion, becauſe all other commnnions are but
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:170270:61"/>dark ſhadowes and reſemblan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of it; the uttermoſt that all Communions among all the creatures amounts to, is but a reſemblance and a dark ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dow of this communion with God: 'Tis reſembled by the Vine and the branches, the head and members, the friend and the friend, the husband and the wife; but alas, theſe are but the fingers of the diall without, to let us ſee how the wheeles move therein: Look how much the ſubſtance out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>goes the ſhadow, ſo much doth the love of Chriſt, and our communion with him, outgo any reſemblance that can be made of it.</p>
               <p n="6">6. Our communion with God, muſt needs be ſuperla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive communion, becauſe all other communions is to be
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:170270:62"/>laid down in order, to the ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king up, and the keeping up of this communion with God: look what fellowſhip ſoever any man hath, or what com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion ſoever he can have, that is inconſiſtent with his communion with God, is all to be laid down for the enjoyment of communion with God; therefore it is the moſt tranſcendent communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</p>
               <p>I might give it you in foure particulars more, there is no communion ſo deſirable, ſo profitable, ſo powerfull, ſo perfect, as this communion with God. This is the firſt property of communion with God, 'tis a tranſcendent com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion.</p>
               <p n="2">II. The ſecond property of the Saints communion with
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:170270:62"/>God, is, that 'tis a free &amp; a vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luntary communion: the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion that the creatures have with God, and that God hath with them, is not brought in by force.</p>
               <list>
                  <item>1. On Gods part to the crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, 'tis free and volun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tary.</item>
                  <item>2. On the creatures part to God, 'tis free and vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luntary.</item>
               </list>
               <p>God makes choice of the creature for communion with himſelfe, for the unveiling of his glory, for the opening of his boſome, for the beſtowing of his love, for the powring forth of his Spirit, God freely and voluntarily opens his bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome to the Saints, and the Saints do freely and volun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tarily open their boſomes to God. <hi>Rev.</hi> 3.20. <hi>Behold, I ſtand
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:170270:63"/>at the dore and knock; if any man hear my voice, and open the dore, I will come in to him; and ſup with him, and he with me.</hi> The dores are not broken open, but they are ſet open when Chriſt comes in; Chriſt comes 'tis true, undeſerved, and many times undeſired, but where he findes not the will free, he makes the will free to embrace him. The will of God is in nothing more ſet forth to the creatures, then in communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and the will of the crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture is in nothing more let out to God, then in commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion alſo: Communion is ſo much the more choice, by how much the more it is choſen. <hi>Cant.</hi> 1.4. <hi>Draw me, and we will run after thee:</hi> When Chriſt drawes, ſhe will not withdraw from him, but ſhe
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:170270:63"/>will follow after him. The ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verall diſpenſations of com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion, ſpeaks it out to be a free communion.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="105-161" type="pages">
               <p n="1">1. Some have a more clear and diſtinct communion with God then others have had: In <hi>Numb.</hi> 12 6, 7, 8. <hi>And he ſaid, if there be a Prophet among you, that I the Lord will make my ſelfe known to him in viſions and dreams: But my ſervant Moſes it is not ſo with him, for I will ſpeak to him mouth to mouth</hi> (that is, apparently, and not in dark ſpeeches) <hi>and the ſimilitude of the Lord ſhall he behold.</hi> Some mens communions are more clear, and leſſe clouded then others: Some men they talk with God face to face, as men talk with their friends; but others, they ſee only the back<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parts of God, communion is
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:170270:64"/>more clouded to them, they cannot enter within the veils; but theſe are taken within all veiles, and they have more naked viewes of Divine glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, then others have: Some ſoules they have ſweet enjoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of communion with God, and yet have not ſo clear diſcoveries, as to be able to demonſtrate their commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion: Whence is this? but be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe communion is free and voluntary, and ſo God diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penceth it according to the rules of his own will.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Some mens communions with God is more conſtant than others; ſome they walk continually in the light of his countenance, and ever ſit un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the hearing of the joyfull ſound; others complain again, as in <hi>Jer.</hi> 14.8. <hi>O the hope of Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael,
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:170270:64"/>the Saviour thereof in the time of trouble, why ſhouldst thou be as a ſtranger in the land, and as a wayfaring man that turneth aſide to tarry for a night?</hi> With ſome God ſtaies but a little while, with others he takes up his dwelling, they are alwaies un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the dew droppings of divine communion, and have the conſtant flowings in of a divine preſence: He lies down with ſome ſoules, and riſeth up with them again. <hi>I have ſet God alwaies before me,</hi> ſaies the Prophet, <hi>he is at my right hand, I ſhall not fall.</hi> God was never out of his ſight, his eye was fixt upon him, his ſoule was running out after him, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 73.23. <hi>Nevertheleſſe, I am continually with thee, thy right hand hath upheld me.</hi> It's a free and voluntary communion.
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:170270:65"/>Though deſires be the actings of the affections, yet they are the iſſuings forth of the will: <hi>Cant.</hi> 4.16. <hi>Awake O North wind, and come thou South, blow upon my garden, that the ſpices thereof may blow out: let my beloved come into his garden, and eate his plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant fruits:</hi> and <hi>Cant.</hi> 7.10. <hi>I am my beloveds and his deſire is to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards me;</hi> there is the going forth of deſires to each other for the enjoyment of one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther: no communion ſo free as the communion that is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt Chriſt and the Saints, between God and his people.</p>
               <p n="3">III. Propertie of communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on that the Saints have with God, it is a very cloſe and neer communion, ſo my Text, <hi>I will meet them and bleſſe them.</hi> Looke as the union that is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt Chriſt and a beleever is
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:170270:65"/>very cloſe and neere, ſo the communion that is betwixt Chriſt and beleevers is very cloſe and neere alſo, they are joyned each to other. There are two things that hinder communion. 1. Difference of perſons. 2. Diſtance of places; both theſe are taken away in Chriſt, when the ſoule comes to approach the preſence of God and ſtand before him, 'tis made one with him, a ſoule cannot ſay as he ſaid in <hi>Numb.</hi> 26.17. <hi>I ſhall ſee him, but not now, I ſhall behold him, but not nigh:</hi> no, this communion it is cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led an appearing before God, it is called a drawing nigh to God, a ſupping with God, it is not a communio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> at a diſtance, but a Communion in pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence, it is not a communion without doors, but a commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion within doores, it is Gods
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:170270:66"/>comming into the Soule, and the Soules comming up more and more into God, <hi>Cant.</hi> 4.16. <hi>Let my beloved come into his garden and eate his pleaſant fruits,</hi> &amp; <hi>Revel.</hi> 3.20. <hi>I wil come in to him and ſuppe with him, and he with me.</hi> It is a Soule creeping into the very boſome of Chriſt, it is as it were the child getting into his Fathers Armes, or the husband lying betweene the breſts of his ſpouſe, as <hi>Cant.</hi> 13. A bundle of Myrthe is my welbeloved unto me, he ſhall lie al night between my breſts; and <hi>Heb.</hi> 10.22. <hi>Let us draw neere, &amp;c.</hi> Obſerve, all com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion is according to the u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion, the farther off any thing is in unio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, the greater diſtance in point of fellowſhip. So it is here, the neearer the union, the cloſer the communion. A child is farther off in point of
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:170270:66"/>union then a ſpouſe, a ſervant farther off then a child, the higheſt union hath alwaies the cloſeſt communion.</p>
               <p>Jeſus Chriſt and the Saints have the neereſt union, for they are made one ſpirit; The bond of all union below is fleſh, but the bond of all union above is ſpirit, Jeſus Chriſt and a Saint is ſo one, as the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther looke? upon them all in him; he never lookes on them as ſubſtracted, but as united.</p>
               <p>There is alwaies the cloſeſt communion where there is the choyceſt love; but there is the choiceſt love betweene Chriſt and the Saints; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the cloſeſt communion. Love cannot live at the leaſt diſtance from its beloved, love lets nothing come between, or interpoſe between it and its
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:170270:67"/>object, it is like a falling moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine that breakes downe all that is betwixt it and its reſt, love is never ſo neere, but it would ſtill be nearer; when it hath got its object, its eye, it would then have it in his Armes.</p>
               <p n="4">IIII. Property of the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion that the Saints have with God; it is a growing and increaſing communion, it eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry day creepes up to a greater height, and to taller ſtature, no communion is capable of ſuch increaſe as our commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion with God. There are two things you may conſider in relation to the ſoules of the Saints: 1. They grow up by co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>munion with God. 2. They grow up in communion with God: the more a Soule con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſeth with God, and the
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:170270:67"/>oftner it doth approach unto him, it comes to ſee a greater beauty in God, to taſt a greater ſweetneſſe in God, and to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joy a greater preſence of God. Conſider three particulars.</p>
               <p n="1">1. Looke how a mans ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehenſion growes of God, ſo his communion growes with God, moſt mens appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henſions are below God, but the beſt mens apprehenſions are too low of God: when men raiſe apprehenſions of God, and with thoughts of the glory and excellency of God upon them, then are they rai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed in their communion with God: As the Soules apprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions of God are raiſed by de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees, ſo his communion with God is raiſed by degrees alſo, <hi>Jſa.</hi> 6.3. The Angels they have glorious acts of communion
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:170270:68"/>with God, they alwaies <hi>behola the face of God,</hi> they are <hi>holy, ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, holy;</hi> when men have low underſtanding, ſlighting thoughts of the glorious Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty of God, and of the holy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of God, they can never enjoy excellent and glorious communion with God; for ſuch as a mans apprehenſions are of God, ſuch is his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion with God. There are 3 things that are according to our apprehenſions of them.</p>
               <list>
                  <item>1. Such as our apprehenſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons are, ſuch will be our eſtimations; as wee ſee things, ſo we prize them.</item>
                  <item>2. Such will be our appli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cations, if they be raiſed towards a thing, we ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply our ſelves to it, that we may have the enjoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of it.</item>
                  <pb n="115" facs="tcp:170270:68"/>
                  <item>3. Such will bee our com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munions: none ſhall ever take delight to draw neere to thoſe things wherein we ſee &amp; judge no excellency.</item>
               </list>
               <p n="2">2. Conſider, as men grow up in conformity to God, ſo will they grow up in commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion with God, for as confor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity is a ground of commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion, ſo the more conformitie the greater the communion ſtill. As the life of holineſſe growes up within us, ſo com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion with God flowes in upon us, <hi>Phil.</hi> 3.10. <hi>That I may know him and the power of his Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrection, &amp;c.</hi> The more con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formable <hi>Paul</hi> was made to Chriſts death, the more com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion he enjoyed in Chriſts Reſurrection. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3. laſt, <hi>We beholding the ſame Image as in a
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:170270:69"/>glaſſe, as the glory of the Lord are changed into the ſame image from glory to glory.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="3">3. The more a Saint growes in largeneſs of affection, the more will he grow up in ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tualneſſe of communion, love drawes the heart ſtrongly af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter God, many waters cannot quench love, neither can the flouds drown it. At the firſt entrance upon our communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on with God, the ſoul is but weak and poor, it hath but ſome taſts of God, but it comes for more, till at laſt it feed upon a full Table. 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2, 3, 4. <hi>If you have taſted that the Lord is gracious;</hi> What then? <hi>to whom comming as unto a living ſtone, diſſallowed indeed of men, but choſen of God, and very precious. Ye alſo as lively ſtones are built up a ſpirituall
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:170270:69"/>houſe.</hi> The more we taſt of the graciouſneſs of God, the more ſtill do we come into commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion with God.</p>
               <p>'Tis very obſervable in the Song of <hi>Solomon,</hi> that the Spouſe at firſt ſhe had but ſome kiſes of the lips of Chriſt, but afterward ſhe is taken in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to his <hi>Chambers,</hi> and at laſt ſhe is brought into his <hi>Banqueting houſe,</hi> into his houſe of Wine. There are foure things that communion leaves in the ſoul, after any precious acts that it hath enjoyed.</p>
               <p n="1">1. Communion leaves in the ſoule a ſweet remembrance in it, <hi>Cant.</hi> 1.4. <hi>The King hath brought me into his chambers, We will be glad and rejoyce in thee, we will remember thy love more then wine.</hi> The Acts of the love of Chriſt ſhewed to a ſoule in
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:170270:70"/>communion with him, is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſed by it. <hi>Pſalm</hi> 42.4. <hi>When I remember theſe things, I power out my ſoule in me:</hi> Theſe things, what things? <hi>when I went with the multitude that kept holy day:</hi> that is, when I went with thy Saints to worſhip thee, where I enjoyed com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion with thee.</p>
               <p n="2">2. It leaves an impreſſion of grace and holineſſe of God upon the ſoule. <hi>Cant.</hi> 5.5. <hi>I roſe up to my beloved, and my hands dropped with mirrh, and my fingers with ſweet ſmelling mirrh upon the handles of the lock. Moſes</hi> his communion left an impreſſion of the glory of God upon him, when he comes from the Mountain, he comes with <hi>his face ſhining:</hi> there are bright beams of Gods face, to be ſeen upon <hi>Moſes</hi> face.</p>
               <pb n="119" facs="tcp:170270:70"/>
               <p n="3">3. It leaves in a man a love to thoſe Ordinances, where he had this communion: O how much is the ſoule in love with thoſe Sermons, in which communion with God is ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained, and with thoſe prayers in which he hath the enjoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of God.</p>
               <p n="4">4. It leaves in the ſoul an inſtinct after further fellow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, and after further com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion; ſo that the whole de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires of the foule are carried forth now after greater and larger enjoyments, after high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er and more glorious incomes, and freſh influences of the divine preſence You never knew what it was to enjoy communion with God, if your hearts run not out after fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther and greater communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</p>
               <pb n="120" facs="tcp:170270:71"/>
               <p>The V. Propertie of com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion and fellowſhip that the Saints have with God in Ordinances, it is ſpirituall and and ſupernaturall. Firſt, it is not all theabilities of nature that can make up this commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion, it is not all the edu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation of the world that can bring a ſoule into the preſence of God; or any parts and gifts that is able to raiſe the Soule into communion with God. It is a ſpirituall communion, it is the Spirit of God co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ming down and taking the Spirits of the Saints up to its ſelfe, <hi>Revel.</hi> 1.10. <hi>I was in the Spirit on the Lords day;</hi> when he was in the ſpirit of the Lord, then he had communion with the Lord, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3. laſt, <hi>we all with open face behold as in a glaſſe the glory of the Lord, are changed into
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:170270:71"/>the ſame Image, &amp;c.</hi> we ſee the glory of the Lord; I but what is the eye by which you ſee it? it is the ſpirit of the Lord. This is an unerring rule, that ſuch as the union is, ſuch the communion muſt be; but the union that is ſpirituall, and therefore the communion that muſt needs bee ſpirituall alſo, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6.17. <hi>They that are joyned to the Lord are one ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. Such as the perſons are enjoying communion, ſuch is the Communion of thoſe per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons: now the perſons enjoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing communion they are ſpirituall perſons, therefore the communion that they en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joy is ſpirituall. God is a ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, and the Saints are ſpiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all, and therefore have com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion one with another in
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:170270:72"/>a ſpirituall manner.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Such as the meanes of communion is, ſuch is the communion it ſelfe; now all the meanes of communion are ſpirituall, therefore the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion it ſelfe muſt be ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall. The Ordinances, they are all of them ſpirituall, they are not carnall Ordinances, though many perſons uſe them carnally. <hi>The words that I ſpeake</hi> (ſaith Chriſt) <hi>they are ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit and they are life;</hi> that is, they be full of vigor, full of pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, full of majeſty, and full of authority. As no meanes at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine their end but ſuch as are ſutable to that end, ſo no end orders the meanes, but ſuch as agree with it. The communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Saints have with God is a ſpirituall communion, and therefore looke into your ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits,
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:170270:72"/>whether or no you doe enjoy communion with God.</p>
               <p>The VI and laſt Propertie of the Communion that the Soule hath with God, it is a delightfull fellowſhip &amp; com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion, the Soule comes to take up its delight and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>placency in the enjoyment of God, when once it is brought into communion with him, and God takes up his delight and complacency in the Soul, when once hee comes to have communion with it. There is no communion ſo delightfull as the communion that is made between God and the Saints. There bee many moſt patheticall expreſſions (in <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lomons</hi> his Song of Songs) hold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing forth the unexpreſſible ſweetneſſe and delight in this communion between Chriſt
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:170270:73"/>and the Soule; but two of them are chiefly remarkable and to be taken notice of, viz. <hi>Cant.</hi> 2.3. and 5.16. The words of the firſt Text are theſe; <hi>As the Apple tree among the trees of the wood, ſo is my beloved among the ſons; I ſate downe under his ſhadow, with great delight;</hi> or as it is in the Hebrew, <hi>I delighted [my ſelf] greatly</hi> (<gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>chimmadti</hi> beeing the conjugation <hi>piel,</hi> which much intendeth and augmenteth the ſignification of the roote;) <hi>and I ſate downe,</hi> or I deſired exceedingly, (for the proper and radicall ſignification of the root <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>chamad,</hi> is, he deſired; and in <hi>piel</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>chimmed,</hi> hee deſired greatly or exceedingly; and <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>chimmadti,</hi> I deſired greatly) and I ſate downe, (to wit to enjoy him and commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:170270:73"/>with him, and to taſt the ſweetneſſe of his fruit; and what followes?) and his fruit was (<gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>matok lechikki</hi>) ſweet to my pallate; accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding as I deſired, which made me to delight my ſelfe abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dantly in the enjoyment of him, and communion with him: That is the force and emphaſis of the firſt text; But further, as if this were not e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough to expreſſe the ſweet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe and delightfulneſſe of this communion; therefore in that other text, <hi>Cant.</hi> 5.16. theſe ſame roots <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>chamad</hi> and <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>matak,</hi> are raiſed up higher, as it were, to expreſſe a higher degree of delight and ſweetneſſe (in this ſpirituall communion between Chriſt and the Soule) thus, <hi>his mouth is moſt ſweet, yea hee is altogether
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:170270:74"/>lovely;</hi> that is the expreſſion in your tranſlation: But the original words (which no tranſlation in the world can reach, nor riſe to) are thoſe; <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>chicko mamtackkim vecullo machamad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dim;</hi> and word for word tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlated they ſund thus, or to this ſenſe; his mouth (<gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>chic-co</hi>) or the place of his mouth (is all) ſweetneſſe, full of (nothing but) ſweetneſſe; for the word <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>mamtakkim,</hi> is a nowne in the plurall num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, importing <hi>dulcedines</hi> ſweetneſſes; that is all ſorts of ſweetneſſe, or ſweetneſſe it ſelfe, and all the ſpecies or kinds of ſweetneſſe are all laid up, and hid as it were in the palate of his mouth to bee ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted by Soules taken up to communion and fellowſhip
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:170270:74"/>with him; that is the force of the firſt word <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>mamtak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kim,</hi> ſweetneſſe, from the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer root <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>matak,</hi> hee was ſweet; and the other word in this text, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>vecullo machamaddim,</hi> hath the like and no leſſe emphaſis, importing this, and he is all, deſires or delights, or all of him, all and every whit or part of him, (<gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>cullo</hi>) is nothing out de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lights (<gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>machamaddim,</hi> being alſo from the former root <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>chamad,</hi> he deſired, a nowne in the plurall number, ſetting forth him, and all the parts of him to bee pleaſures and delights, that is moſt plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant, moſt lovely and delight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full; even to be all delights) and deſires, that is moſt deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable and moſt worthy to bee the object of all deſires; and
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:170270:75"/>therefore he is called <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>chemdat col haggojim, the deſire of all nations; Hag.</hi> 2.8. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>zeh dodi,</hi> this, and ſuch is my beloved, ſo ſweet, &amp; ſo de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lightfull is the taſting of his fruit, in the enjoyment of him, &amp; communion with him; ſaith the beleeving ſoule, to invite all the daughters of <hi>Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruſalem</hi> to come and partake of ſuch exceeding delight and ſweetneſſe, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>betzillo,</hi> under his ſhaddow; for no ſhaddow yields ſuch ſhelter, no ſhad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dow yeelds ſuch comfort, as the ſoule ſitting under Chriſt as a ſhaddow; that is enjoying her communion and fellow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip with him. What delight doth the tender Father take to have communion with his beloved child? and the loving husband take to have com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion
<pb n="129" facs="tcp:170270:75"/>with his beloved wife? what delight doe friends take in having co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion with each other? O how much more, and how much higher is the delights of Chriſt raiſed in having communion with the Saints, and the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lights of the Saints raiſed in enjoying communion with Chriſt. And hence in the ſame chapter, <hi>Cant.</hi> 2.14. The <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ice of Chriſt to the Church, is thus, <hi>O my dove! that art in the clifts of the Rocks, in the ſecret pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of the ſtaires, let me ſee thy countenance, let me heare thy voice, for ſweet is thy voice, and thy coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance is comly.</hi> So much for the properties of communion.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, I come to the acts of communion; and they are many and various: Ile name the chiefe of them.</p>
               <pb n="130" facs="tcp:170270:76"/>
               <list>
                  <item>1. Mutuall manifeſtation.</item>
                  <item>2. Mutuall contemplation.</item>
                  <item>3. Mutuall admiration.</item>
                  <item>4. Mutuall delight and ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfaction.</item>
                  <item>5. Mutuall communication of ſecrecy.</item>
               </list>
               <p>The firſt act of communion is manifeſtation, and that
<list>
                     <item>1. Of God to man.</item>
                     <item>2. Of man to himſelfe.</item>
                  </list>
               </p>
               <p n="1">1. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>f God to man, and that three waies of his Preſence, of his Glory, and of his Grace.</p>
               <p n="1">1. Of his preſence Saith <hi>Jacob, Gen.</hi> 28.16. <hi>God is in this place.</hi> And <hi>John</hi> 14.21. <hi>I will manifeſt myſelfe to him.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. Of his glory, <hi>Pſalm</hi> 63.3: <hi>Ioſee thy power, and thy glory, ſo as I have ſeen thee in the Sanctua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="3">3. Of his grace, <hi>Heb.</hi> 4.16.
<pb n="131" facs="tcp:170270:76"/>
                  <hi>Let us come boldly to the throne of grace, &amp;c.</hi> God in Goſpell-Ordinances through Jeſus Chriſt, ſits upon a Throne of grace; and when we go unto the throne of grace to receive from him, we muſt go with boldneſſe. Now there are two chief acts that you are to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſe about this preſence of God, when it manifeſts it ſelf to you in the uſe of Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances.</p>
               <p n="1">1. The foule ſees and ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerves this preſence of God, manifeſting it ſelfe, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holds it. It is <hi>Davids</hi> wiſh <hi>Pſal.</hi> 27.4. <hi>That I might dwell in thy Houſe, to behold the beauty of the Lord, and to enquire in his Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple.</hi> As the Ordinances of God are the glory of a people, ſo the preſence of God is the glory of the Ordinances, and the
<pb n="132" facs="tcp:170270:77"/>ſoule that enjoyes commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion with God, it eyeth and ſeeth the glorious preſence of God in Ordinances.</p>
               <p n="2">2. There's not only an act of beholding, but there's an act of adoring the preſence that we do behold, doing homage to it: The Angels that have a more immediate communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on with God then we have, they fall down before God, and adore him. And ſo the Prophet <hi>Eſay, Eſay</hi> 6.5. <hi>Then ſaid I, wo is me, for I am undone, becauſe I am a man of uncleane<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lips; for mine eyes have ſeen the King, the Lord of hoſts.</hi> And <hi>Rev.</hi> 4.10. <hi>And the twenty foure Elders caſt down their Crowns at his feet, and fall down before him, &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Secondly, there's an act of Revelation of man to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe,
<pb n="133" facs="tcp:170270:77"/>to know himſelfe. Man in himſelf, is dark in diſcoveries of himſelf, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.6. <hi>For God, who commanded the light to ſhine out of darkneſſe, hath ſhined in our hearts, to give the light of the knowledge of the glory of God, in the face of Jeſus Christ. Prov.</hi> 20.27. <hi>The ſpirit of a man is the can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle of the Lord, ſearching all the inward parts of the belly.</hi> 'Tis not the preſence of the Lord in heaven, but the preſence of the Lord in Ordinances that is the candle of the Lord. Now in this act of the Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation of man to himſelfe.</p>
               <p n="1">1. It diſcovers the ſecrets of the heart, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 14.25: <hi>And thus are the ſecrets of the heart made manifeſt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. It diſcovers the princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples, and grounds, and ends of his action; the Word of
<pb n="134" facs="tcp:170270:78"/>God diſcovers it to him, and the preſence of God in it.</p>
               <p n="3">3. It paſſeth a ſentence up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on a man according to that light, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 20.3.4. <hi>Son of man, wilt thou judge them?</hi> that is, by Ordinances. A ſoule is then judged by Ordinances: Firſt, When it is mightily a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhamed in the Divine pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence, for its non-conformity unto God: and Secondly, when it takes the judgement that the word gives, and lies down with ſilence under it. This is the firſt act of com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion, an act of manifeſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of God to man, of man to himſelfe: Of God to man, of his Preſence, of his Glory, of his Grace: Of man to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, in the ſecrets of his heart, and in the principles and grounds of his heart.</p>
               <pb n="135" facs="tcp:170270:78"/>
               <p>The ſecond act of commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion, is mutuall contempla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, the ſoule doth continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally converſe with Chriſt by ſecret meditation and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>templation. There is a be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holding of the beauty of Chriſt, which is called the beauty of holineſſe: Holineſſe is the beauty of a Saint, and Chriſt is the beauty of holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs. The Saints ſet forth Chriſt to be <hi>the faireſt of ten thouſands, fairer then the children of men,</hi> Chriſt replies again, <hi>O thou faireſt among women.</hi> The Saints they behold and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>template the beauty of Chriſt; and Chriſt, he beholds the beauty, and contemplates the excellency of the Saints: The Saints, they are taken up with the love of Chriſt, and Chriſt he is taken up with the
<pb n="136" facs="tcp:170270:79"/>love of them: thus they ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mire the vertues one of ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. You know, 'tis never well with friends unleſs they be together; what a ſhift will lovers make to enjoy each other? So it is between the Soule and the Lord, <hi>Pſalm</hi> 139.18. <hi>When I awake, I am ſtill with thee:</hi> Why? a man might have told <hi>David,</hi> God is in heaven, and thou art upon the earth. In my bodily preſence I am from him, not with him; but in the preſence of ſpirit, and in the meditation and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>templation of ſoule, I do ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver ly down, I do never riſe up, but I am with thee. By the Covenant of Grace, and the Ordinances of the Goſpell, you are come to God, the judge of all things; you have intimate fellowſhip with him,
<pb n="137" facs="tcp:170270:79"/>as well as with the Saints. <hi>Auſtin</hi> ſaith, The ſoule doth often and familiarly walk the ſtreets of the new <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> Seeing there the Patriarchs, and the Prophets, and the Lord Jeſus Chriſt: This the ſoule doth by fiduciall reaſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, and by high and glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous meditation and contem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plation.</p>
               <p>The third act of communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on is mutuall admiration, the ſoule is admiring thoſe excellencies that are in God, and Chriſt is admiring thoſe excellencies, and being ravi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed with the beauties that are in them. <hi>Thou haſt raviſhed my heart, my Siſter, my Spouſe, Cant.</hi> In the Book of <hi>Exodus,</hi> 'tis ſaid, the High Prieſt carried the names of the children of <hi>Iſrael</hi> upon his Breaſt-plate: A Jew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ell
<pb n="138" facs="tcp:170270:80"/>ſet in the Breaſtplate of Chriſt, O how ſhining and glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious is it! The Saints, as Jewells, are very taking, but being ſet in Chriſts Breaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plate, are more taking: <hi>This is my beloved, this is my friend, O you daughters of</hi> Jeruſalem.</p>
               <p n="4">4. The fourth act of com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion between Chriſt and the ſoule, doth conſiſt in mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall delight, ſatisfaction, contentment, and rejoycing in each other. There was a great fellowſhip and commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion betwixt <hi>David</hi> and <hi>Jona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>han,</hi> and they rejoyced in each other. There's a great fellowſhip and communion betwixt wife and huſband, <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>her be as the loving hind to thee:</hi> and <hi>Eſay</hi> 62.5. <hi>I will rejoyce over thee, as a Bride-groom rejoyceth
<pb n="139" facs="tcp:170270:80"/>over the Bride.</hi> O the content<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment that the ſoule takes in Chriſt, and the contentment Jeſus Chriſt againe takes in the ſoule that he hath commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion withall, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 53.11. <hi>Hee ſhall ſee of the travell of his ſoule, and ſhall be ſatisfied: Pſal.</hi> 17. laſt. <hi>I ſhall bee ſatisfied when I awake, with thy likeneſſe.</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>chelek Jehovah guammo;</hi> The <hi>Lords portion is his people:</hi> in <hi>Deut.</hi> 32.9. and ſo <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>chelki Jebovah amerah naphſhi.</hi> The <hi>Lord is my portion ſaith my ſoule, Lam.</hi> 3.24. therefore the Soule ſtudies Chriſt, and Chriſt ſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies the Soule, the king ſhall take pleaſure in thy beauty: you know the command is unto a man, <hi>Prov.</hi> 5.19. con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning his wife, <hi>let her breſts
<pb n="140" facs="tcp:170270:81"/>ſatisfie thee at all times, and bee thou raviſhed alwaies with her ſoule,</hi> now the Lord Chriſt his people ſatisfie him at all times, it is all the portion hee lookes for, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 62.4. hee calls her name <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>chephtzi bah,</hi> or <hi>Hephzibah,</hi> my delight in her.</p>
               <p n="5">5. Act of communication is communication of ſecrets, love gives gifts, and it gives counſells too. The carriage of a Saint in communion, when he receives the commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nication of Secrets muſt bee thus.</p>
               <list>
                  <item>1. He muſt come with holy and ſanctified thoughts of God.</item>
                  <item>2. He muſt come with ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehenſions &amp; thoughts of his owne vileneſs; To
<pb n="141" facs="tcp:170270:81"/>him will I look (ſaith God) that is of an hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble heart: With an eye of inſpection? no, but with an eye of reſpect, with an eye of compaſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and with an eye of approbation.</item>
                  <item>3. He muſt come with ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riouſneſſe of ſpirit, and with ſolidity of heart to the Ordinances, if he would enjoy communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on with God in them, and have the ſecrets of God revealed to him.</item>
                  <item>4. All a mans graces ſhould be acted, when he comes to attend upon God. And</item>
                  <item>5. He muſt bring the Lord Jeſus Chriſt in his armes: as we perform no ſervice but by him, ſo we have no communion with God
<pb n="142" facs="tcp:170270:82"/>but through him. Chriſt is a two fold Mediator: Firſt of reconciliation for enemies and ſtrangers: Secondly, for communion, and commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nication of ſecrets to thoſe that are reconciled.</item>
               </list>
               <p>Now in all thoſe, and all other acts of ſpirituall communion, there is one ſpeciall and choice qualification of them, that they are performed and acted with much intimacy, or with very intimate and fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miliar correſpondence be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween Chriſt and the ſoule, which appears in theſe par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticulars.</p>
               <p n="1">1. The ſoule hath a great deal of intimacy in thoſe acts of communion with Chriſt; for it lookes upon him as re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conciled, as one that bears nothing but good will to it.
<pb n="143" facs="tcp:170270:82"/>It's ungodly men that look upon God as a ſtranger, God ſhewes them the back, and not the face, <hi>Jer.</hi> 18.17. but 'tis not ſo with his people, he doth remove all clouds, he ſhewes them his face, he doth cauſe his face to ſhine upon them, <hi>Pſalm</hi> 104.37. <hi>My me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditations of him ſhall be ſweet.</hi> Mark what is that which ſweetens <hi>Davids</hi> meditation of the Lord? Truly the reaſon was this, becauſe he looked upon God as re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conciled and at peace with him, therefore whatſoever was in God, was his. Not to look upon God as a Judge, but as a husband, as a Father reconciled, and ſo the ſoule hath an intereſt in whatſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver is his. Thus God is ſaid <hi>Pſalm</hi> 116.7. to be the reſt of
<pb n="144" facs="tcp:170270:83"/>
                  <hi>the</hi> ſoul, <hi>Return to thy reſt, O my ſoul.</hi> Thy reſt, for truly whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the ſoule wanders from God, it is reſtleſſe. That's an excellent expreſſion, <hi>Pſalm.</hi> 38.10. <hi>My heart panteth,</hi> you read it; but in the Originall it is thus, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>libbi ſecharchar;</hi> my heart went about to and fro like a Merchant: For it is from the root <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>ſachar,</hi> which ſignifieth to go about, or to run hither and thither, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perly to traffick, and play the Merchant in buying and ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling: So the ſoule runs to this creature, and is trading with that creature: But when once the ſoule pitcheth upon God, it reſts there as upon a rock of ages.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Their fellowſhip with Chriſt is in things of the high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt nature, therefore there's a
<pb n="145" facs="tcp:170270:83"/>great deal of intimacy. A man may have acquaintance in or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary things, but familiarity in things of the higheſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cernment, muſt needs argue a great deal of intimacy, your fellowſhip is in the Spirit. As the Devill is an enemy to your fellowſhip with God in heavenly things, and things of Eternity, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 6.12. So the intimacy you have with Jeſus Chriſt is in things ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall, and of an eternall con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cernment, and they are theſe foure.</p>
               <p n="1">1. 'Tis fellowſhip with Chriſt in his graces, in the graces of his ſpirit, <hi>We have an Unction from the holy one,</hi> 1 <hi>John</hi> 2.22.</p>
               <p n="2">2. 'Tis fellowſhip with Chriſt in the motions of his ſpirit; they that have received the ſpirit of Chriſt, are led by that
<pb n="146" facs="tcp:170270:84"/>ſpirit, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.14.</p>
               <p n="3">3. 'Tis fellowſhip with Chriſt in the ſealings of his ſpirit, <hi>Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter you believed, you were ſealed by the ſpirit of promiſe. Epheſ.</hi> 1.13.</p>
               <p n="4">4. 'Tis fellowſhip with Chriſt in the earneſt of his ſpirit, which I think is more then the ſealing: ſealing puts the ſtate out of controverſy, but earneſt gives a man a taſt of that glory before hand. As a wicked man in this life, by the ſpirit of bondage doth receive a judgment, a kind of ſenſe and taſt of hell in his ſoule before hand, <hi>Heb.</hi> 10.27. So doth the Lord let into the ſouls of his people a fore-taſt of glory; Here is a great deale of familiarity.</p>
               <p>In the third place, this inti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>macy that the Saints have with the Lord Jeſus conſiſts
<pb n="147" facs="tcp:170270:84"/>in this, they do come to him with boldneſſe, and have ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſe with boldneſſe to the Throne of grace: It is called <hi>drawing neer, Heb.</hi> 10.22. All ungodly men, they ſtand afar off from God, he comes to God as a ſtranger, he is afraid of him: But the drawing neer of the children of God, it is called <hi>Job</hi> 22.26. <hi>A liſting up their face to God:</hi> They ſhall have boldneſs in the preſence of God, as a man that lifts up his face without fear in the preſence of his intimate and familiar friend, <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 14.6, 7. <hi>Their ſmall ſhall be as the Wine of Lebanon.</hi> It is an obſervation of <hi>Galen,</hi> all other things grow old, and will grow the worſe for time; but Wine, the longer you keep it, the better will it be, time doth not make
<pb n="148" facs="tcp:170270:85"/>it grow worſe; and that is the reaſon of that expreſſion of our Saviour, <hi>He that hath taſted of old Wine doth not by and by de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire new.</hi> Now they ſhall come into the preſence of God, and their ſervices ſhall be accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted of him, as the Wine of <hi>Lebanon:</hi> What is that? That is, (as one ſaith) the older they be, and the oftner they come into the preſence of God, the more acceptation they finde with him, becauſe their ſmell is as the Wine of <hi>Lebanon.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In the fourth and laſt place, they have a great deal of inti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>macy which appears in this, they are alwaies calling one another to further fellowſhip, and are never ſatisfied. Our Saviour Chriſt is alwaies cry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, <hi>Open to me my Love, my
<pb n="149" facs="tcp:170270:85"/>Siſter, and my Spouſe;</hi> and the Church ſhe is alwaies calling, <hi>the Spirit ſaith come, and the Bride ſaith come; come away my beloved, come away like a Roe, or a young Hart upon the mountain of ſpices:</hi> By theſe Mountains of ſpices, I conceive to be meant the promiſes; and the Lords making haſt upon them, is for the accompliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of them. <hi>Set me as a Seal upon thine heart.</hi> All this <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing elſe, but the Church ſtill calling to the Lord for further fellowſhip. True grace is a ſpark begun here, and it will never ceaſe aſpiring, till it hath got to him that is the fountain of all in glory.</p>
               <p n="4">IIII. I come to the ends of communion, why God will have any fellowſhip at all with the Saints: and ſeeing he will
<pb n="150" facs="tcp:170270:86"/>have fellowſhip and commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion with them, why he doth not immediately tranſlate them to glory.</p>
               <p>Obſerve; he that accompli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſheth the beſt and the greateſt ends, is the wiſeſt man: the more ends any action accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliſheth, the more excellent is that action. <hi>Mordecai's</hi> acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on was a moſt excellent one, becauſe it brought about ſo man y<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>nds; there was a great plot defeated, great enemies ſubdued, the ſtate of the Church was reſtored, the Kings affections rectified, and himſelfe honoured and advanced. There are eleven ends why God will have fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowſhip and communion with his people.</p>
               <p>The firſt great end of God in communion, is, that he
<pb n="151" facs="tcp:170270:86"/>might manifeſt and impart himſelfe to the creature: Gods imparting of himſelfe to the creature, as it is an act of communion, ſo it is the very end of communion too, <hi>John</hi> 14.21. <hi>I will come to him, and manifeſt my ſelfe to him.</hi> There were two ends for which God created the Angells; the one was for glory, and the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther was for communion; that they might behold his face: and that he might impart himſelfe to them. There is a double end of communion; ſome have communion for need, others have it for de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light; ſome have communion for need, they impart their wants to have them ſupply<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed; others have communion for delight, their communion is out of abundance of deſire
<pb n="152" facs="tcp:170270:87"/>for communication; not that they might receive from o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, but that they might give to others. God hath not communion with the creatures out of need, but out of de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light, not that he needs the creature, but that he might give forth of his abundance to the creature. <hi>God ſets apart the man that is godly for himſelfe,</hi> not for ſervice only, but for communion and communica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion alſo. This is one of the great ends of God in commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion, that he might impart and communicate himſelfe unto the creature. The</p>
               <p n="2">2. End why God will have communion with the Saints, is this; that he might thereby ſet forth unto the Saints, the perfection of the mediation of Chriſt, and that in theſe two
<pb n="153" facs="tcp:170270:87"/>things; 1. In his being able to cure all the wounds and brui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes that ſin had made upon a man: By ſin we loſt both our Image and our fellowſhip. Now Jeſus Chriſt, he doth not only make peace with God, ſo that he doth not de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy us, but raiſeth a way of communion with God to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive us. That's a type of Chriſt, <hi>Exod.</hi> 25.22. <hi>I will meet with thee, and I will commune with thee from above the mercy ſeat, &amp;c.</hi> 2. He is able to give you a more perfect commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion then <hi>Adam</hi> had, as he gives you a more perfect righteouſneſſe. As we have not a diſtinct righteouſneſſe from Chriſts righteouſneſſe, ſo we have not a diſtinct fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowſhip from Chriſts fellow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip. All the communion that
<pb n="154" facs="tcp:170270:88"/>Chriſt hath in the humane nature with the Father, 'tis for us, and in our behalf.</p>
               <p n="3">3. End why God will have fellowſhip and Communion with us, is this, that in this fellowſhip all other fellow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhips may have their founda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions laid, there had never been any kind of fellowſhip if there had not been firſt this kind of fellowſhip: when you brake with God, all Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures brake with you, for up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the ſame termes that wee ſtood with God did all Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures ſtand with us: the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vills they have no fellowſhip among themſelves, other creatures that are ſeparated from God, they have no fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowſhip at all; But now the Saints of Jeſus Chriſt have fellowſhip with the Angells,
<pb n="155" facs="tcp:170270:88"/>I, with all the Saints, they ſhall ſit down with <hi>Abraham, Iſaac,</hi> and <hi>Jacob</hi> in the Kingdom of Heaven They have fellowſhip with the Angells, <hi>Jacobs</hi> Ladder which is Jeſus Chriſt, there the Angells come down and go up again; and they have fellow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip with the Saints, the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion between Saints and Saints, is bottomed upon the Communion that is between Chriſt and Saints, <hi>Eph.</hi> 1.10. <hi>That in the diſpenſation of the fulneſſe of times, hee might gather together in one all things in Chriſt, both which are in Heaven, and which are on Earth, even in him.</hi> The</p>
               <p n="4">4. End why God will have communion with his Saints, that hee might confirme them and make them like unto him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe; God loves to ſee his owne picture upon his owne
<pb n="156" facs="tcp:170270:89"/>people. The more any man is moulded into the ſorry things of this world, the more like them he is: the more commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion he hath with them, the more conformity. Hee that <hi>walkes with the wiſe ſhall be wiſe,</hi> So it is with the Saints, the communion they have with God, the more conformity they have to him, for commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion makes conformitie and carries it on to a greater height: what is the reaſon the Angels are more holy then men? it is becauſe they have more communion with God then men have; what is the reaſon the glorified Saints are more holy then the gracious Saints are? 'tis becauſe they have more Communion with God: What's the reaſon one Saint is more holy then ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther?
<pb n="157" facs="tcp:170270:89"/>'tis becauſe he hath more Communion with God then the other; according to the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree of our Communion, ſuch will be the degree of our ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſs and conformity to God.</p>
               <p n="5">The fifth end of Gods Communion with the Saints is, that hee may act and ſtrengthen their graces, <hi>Cant.</hi> 1.12. <hi>While the King ſitteth at his Table, my ſpikenard ſendeth forth the ſmell thereof.</hi> Every thing the nearer it comes to it's Center, the ſwifter it moves; Communion with God, and the Souls enjoyment of God, 'tis the very Center of it, and and the nearer it comes to this, the ſwifter ſtill it moves. 'Tis obſervable of <hi>Abraham,</hi> that he put forth the greateſt Acts of humility in his Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion with God, <hi>O Lord I am
<pb n="158" facs="tcp:170270:90"/>but duſt and aſhes;</hi> and <hi>Jacob</hi> hee put forth the higheſt Acts of zeal in Communion with God, <hi>I will not let thee go except thou bleſſe me:</hi> and <hi>Moſes</hi> put forth the greateſt Acts of pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er in his Communion with God, O Lord pardon the ſin of this people which is very great: one of the great ends that God aimes at in Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion, is, the exerciſe of your graces, he would not have the graces of his people to lie ſtill, to bee like ſwords ruſting in the ſcabbards, but he would have them exerciſed; hee would have your patience ſet at work in waiting upon him, your faith ſet a work in reſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing on him, your zeal ſet a work in longing after him, your zeal ſet a work in acting for him. God doth not love
<pb n="159" facs="tcp:170270:90"/>any Heavenly Talent ſhould be wrapt up in a napkin; hee was a ſinful ſervant that was a floathful ſervant that laid up his Maſters Talent, when he ſhould have laid out his Maſters Talent: God loves to ſee us exerciſe all our graces, and thence it is that he hath Communion with us.</p>
               <p n="6">6. End why God will have fellowſhip and Communion with his Saints is, that hee may ſweeten the whole courſe of our lives: while we are in this world we meet with many bitter things, and 'tis only Communion with God that can put ſweetneſſe into them. Jeſus Chriſt he was a man of ſorrowes, and what upheld his life? onely Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion with God, <hi>the Lord stood by me and ſtrengthned me.</hi>
                  <pb n="160" facs="tcp:170270:91"/>Now that which upheld the life of Chriſt, that is it that doth uphold the life of every Chriſtian, and that is commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion with God. The ſame words <hi>Paul</hi> makes uſe of, <hi>The Lord ſtood by me, and ſtrengthened me, whoſe I am, and whom I ſerve.</hi> This is the mighty end that God aimes at in communion, that he may ſweeten all the courſe of our pilgrimage, while we are going to heaven. This is the bunch of grapes that God gives his people to feed upon in their wilderneſſe ſtate, they would be out of heart, if they had no com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion with him: This is that ſweet wood, that is caſt into the waters of <hi>Marah,</hi> to make them ſweet and pleaſant.</p>
               <p n="7">7. Therefore hath God communion with his people,
<pb n="161" facs="tcp:170270:91"/>that he may prepare their hearts for deſertions; that they may be affected with them when they come, and that they may not be dejected un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der them though they long continue, that they may not think their cloud ſhall never be blown over, though their Sun be hidden.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="161-212" type="pages">
               <p n="1">1. That they may be affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted with deſertions. Saith <hi>David, Thou didſt hide thy face, and I was troubled.</hi> If he had never ſeen the face of God, he would never have been troubled for Gods hiding of his face. The Saints of God, if they had not ſome taſts of communion with him, they would never be troubled for his withdrawment from them. 2. That they may not be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jected under them: <hi>David,</hi> he
<pb n="162" facs="tcp:170270:92"/>calls to minde his ſong that he made in the night, and the remembrance of that was ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding ſweet, and exceeding pleaſant unto him; the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membrance of former com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munions that he had with God, bore up his ſpirit, when many troubles were up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on him.</p>
               <p n="8">8. End why God will have communion with his people, it is to put them out of taſt with all the pleaſures of ſin and the creature, <hi>Phil.</hi> 4.7. <hi>And he peace of God which paſſeth all understanding, keep your hearts and minds, &amp;c.</hi> 'Tis uſuall, when any epithite of God is added to a thing, it ſignifies and notes the excellency of it: it's the peace of God, a peace that comes from God, a peace that brings to God, a peace
<pb n="163" facs="tcp:170270:92"/>that makes us live like God, in ſuch ſweetneſſe, and peace, and contentment. Now this peace, it puts a mans mouth out of taſt of any of the ſweet neſſes and of the pleaſures of ſin, <hi>Thy loving kindneſſe is bet<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e, then life,</hi> ſaith <hi>David.</hi> And, <hi>Let him kiſſe me with the kiſſes of his mouth, for thy love is better than Wine,</hi> ſaith the Church. There is nothing puts us out of taſt with the pleaſures of ſin ſo much, as a ſoules taſting of communion with God: when a ſoule hath drank the old wine, it cares not for drinking of new, becauſe the old was better. The loving kindneſſe of God in communion with him, is that which takes off the pallate from taſting ſweet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe any where elſe. The more any ſoule is brought in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to
<pb n="164" facs="tcp:170270:93"/>communion with God, the more doth it diſreliſh the plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures of ſin.</p>
               <p n="9">9. End that God aims at in giving the Soule Coumunion with himſelf, is, that it might aggravate their ſins in the day of Repentance: Sins againſt Communion are great aggra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vations. <hi>Solomon</hi> departed from the Lord when hee had appeared to him twice, which migh tily aggravated his ſin. 1 <hi>Kings</hi> 11.9. God kept an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>act account of his manifeſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, that he might aggravate <hi>Solomons</hi> ſins in the day of his Repentance. O when a ſoule comes to fit down and conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, I have not onely ſinned againſt ſo many mercies of God, and ſo long tired out the Patience of God, but I have ſinned againſt Communion
<pb n="165" facs="tcp:170270:93"/>with God, Jeſus Chriſt took me into his <hi>banquetting houſe, and his banner over me was love, He ſtay'd me with flagons, he com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forted me with Apples, his left hand was under my head, and his right hand did imbrace me;</hi> and yet I finned my ſelf out of the ſweet imbraces of Chriſt. O how doth this melt the heart when it comes to mourn for ſin, the ſenſe of the ſweetneſs of his communion that he had with God, puts double tears into his eyes, and double ſighs into his ſpirit. There's no ſuch aggravation of ſin as commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion with God.</p>
               <p n="10">10. Therefore God hath communion and fellowſhip with his people, therefore doth he meet them that he might bleſſe them, <hi>Exod.</hi> 20.24. Communion times are
<pb n="166" facs="tcp:170270:94"/>times when all requeſts are granted. King <hi>Ahaſuerus</hi> grants the requeſt of <hi>Heſter,</hi> when he comes to ſit with her at a ban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quet of wine. The greateſt bleſſing that ever the Saints do enjoy, it is in times of communion with God: O then, how are their conſcien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces filled with peace! O how are their hearts filled with joy! God makes large diſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>butions of ſpirituall bleſſings, when he admits the ſoul into communion with himſelfe: What bleſſing is there that the ſoule may not have, when it hath communion with God in Ordinances?</p>
               <p n="11">11. End of Gods commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion with his people here, is, that his fellowſhip here may be the firſt fruits of glory here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after. When God will beſtow
<pb n="167" facs="tcp:170270:94"/>any great mercy upon a man, he gives him a taſt of it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore hand, that he may ſet him upon more earneſt and eager longings after it. Gods people they have the firſt fruits of all their mercies in this world, and the full crop of them all in another world. When the ſoule is made to taſt of the ſweetneſſe of com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion with God, O how it longs to be with God, how many prayers doth the ſoule make to God, that he would tak it home to himſelfe, that it might ever lye in his arms, and ever dwell in his pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence! <hi>I deſire to be diſſolved, and to be with Chriſt, which is best of all:</hi> What was the ground that raiſed up ſuch deſires in <hi>Paul</hi> to be with Chriſt? It was becauſe here he had taſted of
<pb n="168" facs="tcp:170270:95"/>the ſweetneſſe of Chriſt; and if Chriſt in this world was ſo ſweet, if a Chriſt on earth was ſo ſweet, then a Chriſt in hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven would be much more ſweet. And on this ground the Church calls to Chriſt, <hi>Make haſt my beloved, and be thou like a Roe or young Hart upon the mountain of ſpices, Cant.</hi> 8.14. And in <hi>Revel.</hi> 22. when Chriſt had told the Church, that he would return again unto her to have more communion with her; ſhe cries out, <hi>Amen, even ſo come Lord Jeſus:</hi> She puts her prayers to Chriſts promiſes, and ſaith, Amen Lord, ſo let it be.</p>
               <pb n="169" facs="tcp:170270:95"/>
               <p>Application.</p>
               <p>THere are three Uſes I ſhal make of this point.</p>
               <p>1. Information: 2. Exami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation: 3. Exhortation.</p>
               <p n="1">1. For Information.
<label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Uſe </seg>1</label> Is it ſo that the main end of God in the eſtabliſhing and ſetting up of Ordinances, is communion with himſelfe? Hence I draw theſe ſix inferences.</p>
               <p n="1">1. Behold here the infinite delight that God takes in the ſociety of all his Saints, that he would ſet up all Ordinan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces for this end, to have com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion with them, and that they might have communion with him; that he might have the enjoyment of them, and that they might come to the participation of him. 'Tis a wonder of mercy, and of
<pb n="170" facs="tcp:170270:96"/>condeſcenſions, that the moſt High ſhould ſtoop to ſuch low perſons: He that had infinite bleſſedneſſe in the ſociety, and in the enjoyment of himſelfe, he that took ſo great a delight in his Son, and in the ſociety of the Angells, that he ſhould take any delight to impart himſelfe unto poor ſinfull duſt and aſhes, to men, nay, to wormes, and no men. When men ſet up variety of means for the accompliſhment of their ends, 'tis a great ſigne, that their hearts are very much ſet upon them. Conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der what variety of Ordinan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces God hath ſet up, for the communication of himſelfe unto believers.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Behold here, what ſhould be the main end of the Saints, in the uſe of all Ordinances;
<pb n="171" facs="tcp:170270:96"/>namely, communion, and fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowſhip with God: look what was Gods end in appointing Ordinances, that ſhould be our end in uſing of Ordinan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces: In praying we ſhould ſeek the face of God, and in hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring, we ſhould hear the voice of God, hear what God the Lord will ſay; and in medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tating, my meditation of thee ſhall be ſweet: and in confe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 145.11. <hi>They ſhall talk of the glory of thy Kingdome, and ſpeak of all thy power.</hi> In re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiving the Lords Supper, what ſhould be a Saints grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt delight in comming to that ſpirituall Banquet? It ſhould be meeting with Chriſt in that Ordinance. We often<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times loſe all the bleſſings of the means, becauſe we pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pound not to our ſelves com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion
<pb n="172" facs="tcp:170270:97"/>with God as the end. Many ſoules that come to Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons, Chriſt may ſay to them as he ſaid to thoſe, <hi>What went ye out into the Wilderneſſe to ſee? a Reed ſhaken with the winde?</hi> You are to do as the wiſe Virgins did, to go forth and meet the Brides groom, and to trim your Lamps for the meeting of him. If communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on be not your end in Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances, Ordinances will be nothing available to you; you will loſe all the Ordinances that you enjoy, except you meet with Chriſt in them.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Is communion with God, the great end of God in Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinances? Hence then learn this, that when commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion with God in Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances is not enjoyed, then the ultimate end of all the
<pb n="173" facs="tcp:170270:97"/>Ordinances is fruſtrated; you loſe the end for which all Preaching, and Praying, and Hearing was ordained; while communion is miſſed, while you have no communion with God, Ordinances never at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain their appointed ends. How ſad is it to uſe the means, and never attain the end, and yet this is the caſe of thouſands of ſoules, that live under choice adminiſtrations, and yet are never brought into a ſtate of communion; they are ſo far from enjoying commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion with God, that they know not what it is to have communion with God, though it be declared to them. How many are there that lye a long time at the pool, and yet ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver ſee any Angell come down to ſtirre the water; that lie by
<pb n="174" facs="tcp:170270:98"/>the ſides of the pool, but are never put into the pool? O how ſad is it, that ſuch excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent Ordinances ſhould loſe their ends, and that we ſhould ſo long have the enjoyment of them, and yet never be bettered by them; that we ſhould never attain thoſe ends for which they were or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dained.</p>
               <p n="4">4. Is it ſo, that the main end of God in eſtabliſhing and ſetting up of Ordinances, is to enjoy communion with himſelfe? then let every ſoul take heed of throwing down of Ordinances, let every ſoul be exceeding tender of the appointments of God, leſt they throw down the means of their communion with God, and live without. God in the world: Though God
<pb n="175" facs="tcp:170270:98"/>hath not tyed himſelfe to Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinances, yet he hath tyed us to Ordinances; and in mine own experience, I have known many men grow worſe, but never any man grew better by the neglecting of Ordinan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces. There is no communion to be had with God but in Ordinances; and therefore if you go from Ordinances, you will be fetched home by a ſmarting rod, if you belong to God. VVhat ever you do, be very tender of Goſpell-Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances: <hi>For if he that deſpiſed</hi> Moſes <hi>his Law dyed without mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy under two or three witneſſes; of how much ſorer paniſhment ſhall they be thought worthy, that tram<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple under foot the blood of the cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant, wherewith they were ſanctifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and count it an unholy thing?</hi> O it's ſad to ſee how many
<pb n="176" facs="tcp:170270:99"/>ſoules there are, that caſt dirt upon thoſe Ordinances, that are the Charriots in which Jeſus Chriſt rides, to take up ſoules into communion with himſelfe.</p>
               <p n="5">5. If communion be the main end of God in ſetting up of Ordinances; Behold then whence it is, and why it is, that the Saints of God are ſo much troubled, when they want the ſenſible enjoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of communion with God: they know the truth of this truth, the Ordinance in its end is loſt to them. When a child goes out to ſeek his Father, and cannot finde him, 'tis a great grief to him: Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lievers go out in Goſpell-Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinances to ſeek after God, and when they cannot finde him, it muſt needs be very
<pb n="177" facs="tcp:170270:99"/>grievous to their ſpirits, <hi>Cant.</hi> 3.1. <hi>by night upon my bed I ſought him whom my ſoul loved, but I found him not:</hi> Divine en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavours do not alwaies meet with Divine ſucceſſes; ſhee ſought him, I, but ſhe found him not. So many a ſoule comes to meet with God in an Ordinance, but God is with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drawn from them, they can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not ſee his face though they come to ſeek his face, and the ſoreſt affliction that a child of God lies under, or can lie un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der in this world, is the with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drawment of God from Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances, when he thinks to find God in them, he is departed from them; they ſhall go with their Flocks and their Herds to ſeek after the Lord, but they ſhall not find him, for he hath withdrawn himſelf.</p>
               <pb n="178" facs="tcp:170270:100"/>
               <p n="6">6. Is it the main end of God in ſetting up Ordinances, that his Saints might have Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion with him? Then learn hence the ground why the Saints ſet ſo high a price upon, and are ſo often found in Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Ordinances, 'tis becauſe they there meet with Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion with God; now the meetings with God is the ground of their ſo often ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearings before him: Alas, 'tis not their meeting together that they aim at, but their meeting with God that they looke after, if God be want<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, all is wanting, if God be there, nothing is wanting. Ordinances alas they can do nothing without God, they are but painted ſwords in dead mens hands, they can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not raiſe the heart when it is
<pb n="179" facs="tcp:170270:100"/>fallen, they cannot refreſh the heart when it is ſad, they can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not enlighten the ſoul when there is a cloud upon it, they cannot draw the heart to Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven when it is earthly, they cannot reſolve any doubts that are upon their ſpirits: no, theſe things are too great, and too good for Ordinances to do, 'tis onely the God of the Ordinances that can do all all theſe things. Alas, if there were nothing but the very Ordinance, believers would never be ſo often in the uſe of them, if there were nothing but a little bread and wine at a Sacrament, who would ſit down at it with ſuch great de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light? If there were nothing but praying in prayer, who would loſe any time about it? if there were nothing but
<pb n="180" facs="tcp:170270:101"/>hearing in hearing, if there was not the power of God going along with the voice of man, what is it? And therefore when you ſee the Saints and people of God ſo often imploying themſelves about ſpirituall Ordinances; when you ſee them begin the day with prayer, and end the day with thankſgivings; when you ſee them fixing their ſouls to meditate upon God, you may well conclude there is more then the bare Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance; nay, in every Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance remember 'tis not for the Ordinance ſake, but for Communion with God which was the main end why God ſet up Ordinances.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Uſe </seg>2</label> For Examination, how you may know whether you have had any fellowſhip
<pb n="181" facs="tcp:170270:101"/>and Communion with God or no.</p>
               <p>This is a ſerious queſtion, and deſerves more then a ſlight anſwer. Communion with God is a thing of more concernment, and of greater moment then moſt men are a ware of, and we uſe to try things that will not be taken from us without tryall. Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider three things:
<list>
                     <item>1. God hath ſcales to weigh all your graces.</item>
                     <item>2. He hath touchſtones to try all your graces.</item>
                     <item>3. He hath Fanns to ſift all your graces.</item>
                  </list>
               </p>
               <p>Rev. 3.2. <hi>thou hast a name to live, and art dead;</hi> And then you uſe to try thoſe things where there may be credit. Sometimes men take that for fellowſhip with God in Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances
<pb n="182" facs="tcp:170270:102"/>which is not; and ſometimes mendeny that for fellowſhip with God in Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances: that is;</p>
               <p>Firſt, Some men take that for fellowſhip with God in Ordinances which is not. There are two things that look like fellowſhp and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion with God in Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances that are not.</p>
               <p n="1">1. There are ſome imper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect approches of God unto the ſoules of unregenerate men in ordinances, when there is no reciprocall approaches of the ſpirits of unregenerate men to God.</p>
               <p n="2">2. When their ſpirits are onely paſſive and not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctive, God calls upon them to ſeek his face, but their hearts never anſwer, <hi>Lord thy face will I ſeek,</hi> as the heart of the righteous do.</p>
               <pb n="183" facs="tcp:170270:102"/>
               <p>Secondly, ſome men deny that for Communion with God in Ordinances which is Common.</p>
               <p>Take theſe two diſtinctions.</p>
               <p n="1">1. <hi>Dist.</hi> Communion with God in Ordinances is ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times ſecret, and ſometimes more manifeſt: Firſt, it is ſecret: God doth not alwaies ſpeak peace with a loud voice, he ſometimes ſpeaks peace with a ſtill voice, <hi>Cant.</hi> 5.4, 5. there Communion with God is more ſecret, <hi>My beloved put in his hand by the hole of the door, and my bowels were moved for him. I roſe up to open to my beloved, and my hands drop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped with mirrhe, and my fingers with ſweet ſmelling mirrhe upon the handles of the locks.</hi> Second<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, It is more manifeſt: ſometimes they are in hidden
<pb n="184" facs="tcp:170270:103"/>rooms, in ſecret chambers to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether. At other times they are walking in the open galleries.</p>
               <p n="2">2. <hi>Diſtinction:</hi> There's a Sanctifying Communion, and there's a raviſhing Communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: The ſanctifying-Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion may be where the raviſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Communion may not be, <hi>Pſ.</hi> 51.8. <hi>make me to of hear joy and gladneſſe, &amp;c. David</hi> hee had a ſanctifying Communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on before, but now he beggs for a raviſhing Communion with God that would raiſe him up to a rejoycing in God.</p>
               <p>Now you may know whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther you have fellowſhip with God in Ordinances or no by three things.</p>
               <list>
                  <item>1. By ſomthing Before duty.</item>
                  <item>2. By ſomthing In duty.</item>
                  <item>3. By ſomthing After duty.</item>
               </list>
               <p>Firſt, by ſomething before
<pb n="185" facs="tcp:170270:103"/>duty. If you have Communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on with God, you may know it by theſe three Characters.</p>
               <p n="1">1. If God before raiſe up thy heart to make fellowſhip thy end in duty. <hi>O ſhew us the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther and it ſufficeth us,</hi> that was the Diſciples end in their prayer to Jeſus Chriſt; ſhew us the Father, nothing but the Father would ſuffice them: So when thou comeſt to Ordinances, and ſayeſt, O that I might ſee the goings of God my King in his Sanctua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry! O that I might be able to ſee the prints and footſteps of God in ſuch and ſuch an Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinance! God will never de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive the expectations of his people; Theſe expectations they are raiſed by him, &amp; they ſhal be fulfilled by him, <hi>Jer.</hi> 29.11. <hi>I know the thoughts that I
<pb n="186" facs="tcp:170270:104"/>think towards you, ſaith the Lord, thoughts of peace, and not of evil, to give you an expected end:</hi> They looked for peace, I, ſaith God, an Olive branch ſhall be ſent them; they expect my pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence, they ſhall find my pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence. If God before hand raiſe up thy heart to make fellow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip thy end in all thy Acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, then thou maiſt certainly conclude thou ſhalt have fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowſhip with him.</p>
               <p n="2">2. If God before hand put thy heart into a ſuitable frame to the duty, then thou maiſt aſſure thy ſoule thou ſhalt have fellowſhip with God in the duty; if thou findeſt thoſe graces exerciſed by thee, the duty calls for from thee. When God called <hi>Moſes</hi> into the Mount, he was ſure to have communion with God:
<pb n="187" facs="tcp:170270:104"/>Why? becauſe God gave him ſuch diſpoſitions, as fitted him for communion. When once the heart is put into commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion frame, it ſhall never go without it: if thy ſhooes be put off, and the place on which thou ſtandeſt be holy ground, never fear, but thou ſhalt enjoy communion with the holy God. There is a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>markable paſſage the Pſalmiſt hath, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 10.17. expreſly pointing at this, that God doth firſt put the ſpirits of his people in a frame, ſuitable to communion with himſelfe: And 2. he commeth unto them with a bleſſing, enclin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing his ear to hear and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept them favourably, or that whenſoever the Lord doth put the hearts of his people into a prepared frame, then he
<pb n="188" facs="tcp:170270:105"/>doth incline his ear and hear them: the words are thoſe, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>tachin libam,</hi> (there is the firſt) thou wilt fit, diſpoſe, direct, or prepare their heart; or thou wilt cauſe their heart to prepare it ſelfe, as it were; for <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>tachin</hi> is the future <hi>hiph.,</hi> from the root <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>chun,</hi> he prepared or fitted, &amp;c. and then obſerve what follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth: VVhen once thou haſt thus fitted and prepared their heart, then <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>takſhib ozn<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>kah,</hi> Thou wilt prepare thy ear to hear; or thou wilt cauſe thy ear to be heard, and to be attentive in hearing their ſuits and ſupplications: for the word <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>takſhib</hi> is alſo future <hi>hiph.</hi> from the root <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>kaſhab inkal,</hi> he was attentive, or he heard with attention. So that God never
<pb n="189" facs="tcp:170270:105"/>puts his people into a prepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red poſture for communion, but he gives them communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. VVhen duties anſwer to our hearts, and our hearts anſwer to our duties: This is the workmanſhip of God, to frame the heart for duty, as well as to cut out duty for the heart. And hence the Pſalmiſt knowing this, that it is the or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der and work of God; firſt, to prepare the heart for commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion, and then to incline his own ear to hear his people, and to entertain communion with them in Ordinances; he doth obſerve this order, and follow it with a practiſe ſuitable to it in his daily ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreſſes to God, that is thus: whereſoever he doth finde his heart put into a fitted and prepared frame for —
<pb n="190" facs="tcp:170270:106"/>communion with God, he doth not let it dye again, and go out of frame by a ſloathfull neglect of ſuch a diſpoſition of heart: No, but he immedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ately ſets himſelfe to duty, to worſhip God, and to the acts of his Worſhip, in his Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances, as he expreſſeth him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf in another Pſalm; <hi>viz. Pſal.</hi> 57.7. thus: <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>Nac<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>on libbi elohim, nachon <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ibbi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>,</hi> (there is the firſt, he finds his heart fitted and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared for communion with God) My heart (ſaith he) is fitted or prepared (for the word <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>nachon</hi> is the paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſive conjugation <hi>niphal,</hi> ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fying, he is fitted or prepared, from the ſame root in the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer Text <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>chun,</hi> he fitted, or prepared in the active; and ſo it is rather to be rendred,
<pb n="191" facs="tcp:170270:106"/>prepared or fitted, then fixed, thus; <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>libbi,</hi> my heart, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>nachon,</hi> is fitted or prepared) O God, my heart is fitted or prepared (for communion with thee.) Well, what fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowes? He preſently ſets him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe upon that great duty and Ordinance of communion with God, in the praiſing of his Name, and ſinging forth thoſe praiſes, as in the words immediately following in the ſame verſe thus: <hi>My heart is pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared, O God, my heart is prepared:</hi> (therefore) <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>Aſhi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dah va-azameral, I will ſing and give praiſe.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="3">3. When the heart is carried forth in its utmoſt ſtrength after duty, then thou ſhalt enjoy communion with God <hi>Dan.</hi> 9.3.22. compared. <hi>Daniel</hi> he ſets his face towards <hi>Jeru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalem,</hi>
                  <pb n="192" facs="tcp:170270:107"/>and the Text ſaith, that <hi>at the beginning, the Angel of th Lord came and touched him: O Daniel, greatly beloved of the Lord, thy prayer is heard.</hi> When the ſoule puts forth his grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt ſtrength in duty, then doth it enjoy moſt commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion with God in duty: The more active thou art in im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ploying thy ſelfe about this work, the more in-comes from God will there be in this work. That's the firſt parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular.</p>
               <p>Secondly, in the duty: If there be raviſhing diſcoveries the heart knowes it, God is his own witneſſe in the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit. I, but if there be but an humbling fellowſhip, though there be not raviſhing diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veries, 'tis an evidence. Now the diſpoſitions of the Soul
<pb n="193" facs="tcp:170270:107"/>in the duty which ſpeaks com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion with God, are theſe.</p>
               <p n="1">1. It is a very humble fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowſhip, it laies a man very low in his own eyes, and rai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth God very high. How ready are we then to cry with <hi>Peter, Lord depart from me, I am a ſinfull man.</hi> The heart will be humble, and the preſence of God will be dreadfull.</p>
               <p n="2">2. The appearance of grace will be powerfull, it will ſet the heart againſt every ſin. When <hi>Moſes</hi> came from the mount of communion, how zealous was he againſt the ſin of Idolatry?</p>
               <p n="3">3. There will be an anſwe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring of the heart, for it is an echoing fellowſhip. The Lord ſaith, thou art my people, and they will ſay, thou art my God: If he ſay, ſeek ye my
<pb n="194" facs="tcp:170270:108"/>face, they will anſwer, thy face Lord will I ſeek.</p>
               <p n="4">4. It will be a heating fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowſhip. The Diſciples ſaid, <hi>Did not our hearts burn within us, while he talked with us?</hi> O it will be a heating fellowſhip, it will kindle freſh flames of love towards Jeſus Chriſt, it will make your ſoules burn to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards heaven.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, after the duty, you may know whether you have fellowſhip by theſe par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticulars.</p>
               <p n="1">1. It will leave a ſweet re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membrance behind it, <hi>Pſalm</hi> 42.4. <hi>When I remembered theſe things, I powre out my ſoul in me; for I had gone with the multitude, I went with them to the houſe of God, with the voice of joy and praiſe, with a multitude that kept holy day.</hi> The ſoul can never
<pb n="195" facs="tcp:170270:108"/>forget thoſe times of commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion that it had with God, nor thoſe boſome embraces, nor thoſe ſweet kiſſes that it had from the lips of Chriſt: Theſe mercies are too great to be forgotten by a ſoule that doth enjoy communion with God.</p>
               <p n="2">2. It leaves an inſtinct in the ſoule after farther fellow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip with God. If a man fall into ſin but once, it leaves a proneneſſe in a man to fall into it again: So 't is in communion with God, if a man enjoy communion with God but once, it leaves a greater prone<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe and aptitude in the man to look after communion with God again. A ſoule that hath had communion and fellow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip with Chriſt, O how doth it long after further fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowſhip
<pb n="196" facs="tcp:170270:109"/>with him.</p>
               <p n="3">3. It leaves in a man a love to thoſe Ordinances wherein it had communion with God: O how is the ſoul in love with thoſe prayers which brought Chriſt to it, and in love with that Word wherein Jeſus Chriſt ſpake to his ſoul: How is it taken with every Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance, wherein the influences of Heaven are diſtilled and drop upon them.</p>
               <p n="4">4. It leaves an impreſſion upon the ſoule of the holineſſe of God. The holineſſe of God is of a transforming nature, <hi>Acts</hi> 4.15. <hi>They took knowledge of them that they had been with Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus.</hi> They ſaw that they had enjoyed communion with God, why? there were ſuch beams of the Majeſty, and the beauty, and the glory of God
<pb n="197" facs="tcp:170270:109"/>left upon them that they that ſaw them might eaſily know, that they had ſeen God, and had enjoyed communion with him: and 'tis ſaid of <hi>Stephen,</hi> they beheld his face as the face of an Angel, when he was before the Councell.</p>
               <p n="5">5. If you have fellowſhip &amp; communion with God, you wil have acquaintance with God, and familiarity with him, <hi>Job</hi> 22.21. <hi>Acquaint thy ſelfe with God, &amp;c.</hi> A ſoule cannot enjoy communion with a ſtranger, till he be familiarized into his acquaintance. Communion ſpeaks the choiceſt familiarity between perſons If your ſouls have had communion and fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowſhip with God, then you are brought into acquaintance with God.</p>
               <p n="6">6. If your ſoules have en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyed
<pb n="198" facs="tcp:170270:110"/>communion and fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowſhip with God, you will be ſure to keep God company, and walk with God, let others walk which way they pleaſe. It is ſaid of <hi>Enoch,</hi> to his praiſe, that he <hi>walked with God;</hi> and God ſpake to <hi>Abraham, Walk before me, and be thou perfect.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="7">7. A ſoul that hath com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion and fellowſhip with God in Ordinances, is ſenſible of all. Gods withdrawments, he knowes when God comes in, and when God goes out at an Ordinance. How many perſons are there that never minde either the acceſſes or receſſes of Chriſt or the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, when they come in to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear before God in Ordinances.</p>
               <p n="8">8. There will be a ſweet a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greement between Chriſt and the ſoul: can two walk toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,
<pb n="199" facs="tcp:170270:110"/>except they be agreed in what path they ſhall go, and what ſteps they ſhall take? that which was Gods way ſhall be the ſoules way, God will not go one way and let the ſoul go an other, then it can have no Communion; But when God and the ſoul tread both in the ſame ſteps, there's a ſweet agreement, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lightful harmony between them.</p>
               <p n="9">9. A ſoul that hath Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion with God, highly pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zeth the preſence of God, and the preſence of the Lord Jeſus Chriſt; <hi>If thy preſence go not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long with us</hi> (ſaith <hi>Moſes</hi>) <hi>carry us not from hence:</hi> and nothing gives the ſoul content, if it hath loſt Communion, till it be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtor'd again, it can bear any thing better then a breach in
<pb n="200" facs="tcp:170270:111"/>its Communion, no loads lie ſo heavy upon it as a departed Saviour: how doth the ſoule lament after the Lord, when it cannot find the Lord? it is reſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe till it come to lie in it's beloveds boſome.</p>
               <p>Laſtly, A ſoul that hath fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowſhip &amp; Communion with God, it cuts off all other contr<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ary fellowſhips that are incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtent with it; cuts off all ſinful &amp; carnal fellowſhip. They wil have no fellowſhip with the unfruitfull works of darkneſſe that have fellowſhip &amp; commu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nion with the Father of lights.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Uſe </seg>3</label> For Exhortation to preſſe you to look after communion with God:</p>
               <p>There are three things that wee are to look after to attain to communion with God.</p>
               <list>
                  <item>1. We muſt have a right path.</item>
                  <pb n="201" facs="tcp:170270:111"/>
                  <item>2. We muſt have a ſtaffe of ſtrength and power.</item>
                  <item>3. Wee muſt have true aſcents and fellowſhips.</item>
               </list>
               <p>Firſt, wee muſt have a right path, and that is Jeſus Chriſt, there is no coming to the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther but by the Son, <hi>J<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>h.</hi> 14.6. <hi>I am the way,</hi> &amp;c. There is a choice way to God, but there are no choice of waies to come to God; paſſe by one you paſs by all: <hi>Heb.</hi> 7.19. <hi>For the Law made nothing perfect, but the bringing in of a better hope did: by <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>he which we draw nigh unto God:</hi> what is that better hope? It is Jeſus Chriſt: hope depends ſo much on him for the beſt things, that he is called our better hope, by which with aſſurance wee may draw nigh to God; that's the Apoſtles incouragement, <hi>Heb.</hi> 10.19.
<pb n="202" facs="tcp:170270:112"/>
                  <hi>by the b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ood of Ieſus we have bold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe to enter into th holieſt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Secondly, wee muſt have a ſtaffe of ſtrength and pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, and that's the ſpirit of God, <hi>Iude</hi> 20 <hi>Verſe,</hi> praying in the Holy-Ghoſt. As it's the office of Chriſt to interceed with God for us, ſo it's the office of the ſpirit to interceed in us; the prayers that go up to God, come down from God. There are two burdens that are too heavy for us to bear;</p>
               <p>Firſt, the burden of ſins.</p>
               <p>Secondly, the burden of ſuits.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, we muſt have true aſcents and footſteps, elſe wee ſhall never come up to Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion with God.</p>
               <p>There are ſix ſeverall aſcents and foot ſteps by which wee
<pb n="203" facs="tcp:170270:112"/>aſcend to the Throne of God for the enjoyment of com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion with him.</p>
               <p n="1">1. The ſence of ſelf-indigen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy: wee never enjoy commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion with the fulneſſe of God, till we ſee the Emptineſſe that is in our ſelves, a full ſoule loaths the hony Come, though it have never ſo much ſweet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe in it, the whole never prizeth the Phyſitians. Medi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cines: ſence of want draws the Creature downe on Earth, and then leads it up to Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Sence of our own utter inability to ſupply our own neceſſities, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 73.25, 26. <hi>Whom have I in Heaven but thee? and there is none upon Earth that I deſire beſides thee: my fleſh and my heart faileth: but God is the strength of my heart, and my
<pb n="204" facs="tcp:170270:113"/>portion for ever.</hi> If there be any thing that you expect ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfaction from beſides God, you will never come to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion with him: you will then looke after fellowſhip with him, when you ſee all your happineſſe in him. The.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Footſtep to Communion with God is ſence of our own unworthineſſe, that God ſhould give ſupplies unto us: when <hi>Jacob</hi> was brought ſo nigh into fellowſhip and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion with God, when hee was ſtrugling with God, and would not let him go till hee had got a bleſſing, then he l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t go all opinion of worth in himſelf to receive a bleſſing, <hi>Gen.</hi> 32.10. <hi>I am not worthy of the leaſt of all thy mercies.</hi> There is no drawing nigh to the
<pb n="205" facs="tcp:170270:113"/>moſt high God without low thoughts of our ſelves: the proud look diſdainfully upon God, and meet with diſdain from him. The</p>
               <p n="4">4. Footſtep to Communion is the clear knowledge and full acknowledgement of the power and ſufficiency of God to help us, and to fill us, <hi>Heb.</hi> 11.6. hee that cometh to God muſt believe that God is, and that hee is a rewarder of them that diligently ſeek him: what's that? It lies in two things.</p>
               <p>Firſt, that God needs no Creature.</p>
               <p>Secondly, that he is enough to ſupply the needs of every Creature.</p>
               <p n="5">5. Fooſtep to communion is, to believe that the Lord ſtands ready to embrace us
<pb n="206" facs="tcp:170270:114"/>in all our commings to him, and to give us all the good that we come for; to believe that he is ready to ſupply us in every good we ſeek from him: we honour God moſt when we expect the greateſt incomes of mercy from him. <hi>He hath not ſaid to the ſeed of Jacob, ſeek ye me</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>thou, for a vain, void, and empty nothing.</hi> The greatneſſe of God gives him power, and his goodneſſe gives him will to ſupply us: therefore we ſhould believe without doubting his rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dineſſe to ſupply us, <hi>Heb.</hi> 10.22. <hi>Let us draw near in full aſſurance, &amp;c.</hi> In what aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance muſt we come? Even in this, that we ſhall be an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered in whatſoever we ask. As Faith muſt be mingled with every word of precept
<pb n="207" facs="tcp:170270:114"/>that Godſpeaks to us, ſo it muſt be mingled with every word of prayer that we ſpeak to him, <hi>James</hi> 1.5, 6. <hi>If any lack wiſdome, let them aske it of God, that giveth to all men lib rally, and upbraideth not.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="6">6. Footſtep of our Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion with God, is bold<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>neſſe in all our approaches to him: As God opens his heart freely, ſo we muſt open our mouths boldly. Holy boldneſſe is the higheſt act of Faith, and the neereſt ſtep to God; when the ſoul is got thus high, it is upon the top of <hi>Jacobs</hi> Ladder, <hi>Heb.</hi> 4.16. <hi>Let us come boldly to the Throne of grace, &amp;c.</hi> Boldneſſe is a grace, that is moſt ſuitable to the Throne of grace. Let me ſpeak with reverence,
<pb n="208" facs="tcp:170270:115"/>we are gotten to Gods ſide, when we come with bold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, grace can ſtep no high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er; the next degree of aſcent is to be ſwallowed up in glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry. In every Ordinance we have a viſion of God by faith; and in every duty, we ſhould come to God with boldneſſe and joy. To conclude all: Would you have Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion with God in Ordinan<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ces? Then let me commend to you theſe five things.</p>
               <p>Firſt, there muſt be a be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing neer to God, before there can be a drawing neer to God; you muſt labour after Reconciliation, before ever you can enjoy Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion; while you are e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemies, you will be ſtran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers. Till God be brought neer to you, you can never
<pb n="209" facs="tcp:170270:115"/>draw neer to God: We are firſt brought neer to God by the blood of Chriſt, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ever we have Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion with God in Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances.</p>
               <p>Secondly, He that deſires Communion with God in Ordinances, muſt look up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on God as preſent, and not as abſent from him, without this, we can never enjoy Communion with him. <hi>Rev.</hi> 4.6. there's a <hi>high Throne,</hi> which is nothing elſe but a repreſentation of God to his people in Goſpell-Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances, there they behold his glory, and enjoy Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion with him. He that deſires Communion with God in Ordinances, muſt look upon God as preſent; firſt, in Majeſty; ſecondly,
<pb n="210" facs="tcp:170270:116"/>in jealouſie; thirdly; in au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority; fourthly, in puri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty.</p>
               <p n="3">3. If you would have Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion with God in Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances, then in every Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance make Communion with God your end. The hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocriſie, or the ſincerity of every mans ſpirit is moſtly ſeen in his end. Theres a dou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble end that every man ſhould propoſe to himſelfe in com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming to Ordinances, and when this end is unpropoſed, Communion with God is un-enjoyed. Firſt, they ſhould do them as acts of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience in reference to Gods command: Secondly, they ſhould uſe them as means of Communion, in reference to Gods promiſe. In every Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinance you ſhould make
<pb n="211" facs="tcp:170270:116"/>Communion with God your end, and uſe the Ordinance as a means for the attainment of that end, thus; I am going to ſuch a duty Lord, and this is my end, to enjoy thee in it. I am going to pray, and I would have the enjoyment of God in prayer. This is the end you ſhould propound, when you go about every Ordinance.</p>
               <p n="4">4. Get divine and ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall apprehenſions, if ever you would enjoy Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion; for according to our apprehenſions of God, ſuch will be our enjoyments of him, and ſuch will be our Communions with him. Some perſons have to do with God in Ordinances, that never think what that God is with whom they have to do. The
<pb n="212" facs="tcp:170270:117"/>only way to raiſe up our Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion with God, is, to raiſe up our apprehenſion of him: if we know him but a little, we can never enjoy much ſociety and communion with him.</p>
               <p n="5">5. Make uſe of former ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>periences, if you would enjoy communion with God: the experience that men have had of the ſweetneſſe of God, will ſtirre up their hearts to long more and more after commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion with God. He that hath taſted of the ſweetneſſe of God, cannot ſit down ſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied, except he meet with God in the Ordinance.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:170270:117"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
